<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Ali Abdaal</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/xavwe/rss-aggregator/refs/heads/main/feeds/ali-abdaal-c88aa20d.xml</link><description>Archived feed from https://aliabdaal.com/feed/</description><item><title>How To Never Be Bored at Work</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/how-to-never-be-bored-at-work/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>The secret to enjoyable work and sustained productivity is to find a way to make what we’re doing a little bit more fun. Now, I fully stand by this approach (it’s even the main idea of my book, Feel-Good Productivity). But, there’s a problem. Some things are just boring. There are things at work that [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/how-to-never-be-bored-at-work/">How To Never Be Bored at Work</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 5 Feb 2025 11:14:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How to build a time management routine</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/how-to-build-a-time-management-routine/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Most of us don’t have time to consistently do the things we truly enjoy. Between work, family, friends, staying healthy, and side projects, finding time to do everything we want can seem impossible. The truth is, without a solid plan, time slips through our fingers. We’re left feeling like we’ve barely made progress on our [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/how-to-build-a-time-management-routine/">How to build a time management routine</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 11:22:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How procrastination affects your daily life</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/how-procrastination-affects-your-daily-life/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Procrastination is a challenge as old as time itself. The philosophers of Ancient Greece even had a term for it: ‘akrasia’. It describes the act of doing something despite it going against our better judgement. These days, procrastination can feel more challenging than ever. We’re surrounded by countless digital distractions and we struggle to get [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/how-procrastination-affects-your-daily-life/">How procrastination affects your daily life</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Outsourcing Will Help You Grow on YouTube</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/youtube/how-outsourcing-will-help-you-grow-on-youtube/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Hiring my first freelancer was a huge step in my YouTube business. For years, it had only been me working on my channel. I was writing scripts, editing videos and uploading consistently on top of my full time job as a doctor in Britain’s National Health Service. Even though I was overwhelmed with work, and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/youtube/how-outsourcing-will-help-you-grow-on-youtube/">How Outsourcing Will Help You Grow on YouTube</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 11:00:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>10 Productivity Tips For New Entrepreneurs</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/10-productivity-tips-for-new-entrepreneurs/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Ever feel like you’re juggling a million things while building your business? Starting a new business is an exciting journey, but it comes with its fair share of challenges. As a new entrepreneur, you’re likely handling multiple things—marketing, finances, customer relations—all while trying to keep your sanity intact. That&#8217;s why mastering effective time management and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/10-productivity-tips-for-new-entrepreneurs/">10 Productivity Tips For New Entrepreneurs</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 6 Jan 2025 14:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Sustainable Productivity and How You Can Achieve It</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/what-is-sustainable-productivity-and-how-you-can-achieve-it/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>In a world obsessed with hustle culture, many of us may find ourselves battling against ‘toxic productivity’. When productivity is associated with getting things done in the most effective way, we can start to confuse productivity with busyness. You might spend a lot of time talking about getting things done &#8211; organising, questioning and analysing [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/what-is-sustainable-productivity-and-how-you-can-achieve-it/">What is Sustainable Productivity and How You Can Achieve It</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 3 Jan 2025 14:00:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>10 Productivity Tips for Creators</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/10-productivity-tips-for-creators/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>The internet never sleeps, and neither do creators. We’re always juggling content creation, a never-ending to-do list and a constant stream of online comments and messages. It seems no matter how hard we work, there&#8217;s always more to be done. For most of us, what started as a fun after-hours project has turned into a [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/10-productivity-tips-for-creators/">10 Productivity Tips for Creators</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 14:00:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What Is Burnout and How To Recover From It</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/what-is-burnout-and-how-to-recover-from-it/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Burnout can affect everyone across all walks of life. It’s a complicated issue that we often associate with overworking, mainly impacting those in super stressful and demanding corporate jobs. But it’s not a problem reserved for a select few . It can happen to any one of us and it doesn’t always stem from working [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/what-is-burnout-and-how-to-recover-from-it/">What Is Burnout and How To Recover From It</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2024 14:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How To Boost Your Productivity and Stay Creative</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/how-to-boost-your-productivity-and-stay-creative/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>We all know the feeling. You’re trying to get through your to-do list, but somewhere along the way, your creativity starts to fizzle out. You’re stuck in that all-too-familiar cycle of trying to be productive but feeling uninspired. But, there’s good news. Staying productive doesn’t have to come at the expense of your creativity. In [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/how-to-boost-your-productivity-and-stay-creative/">How To Boost Your Productivity and Stay Creative</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2024 14:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>5 Ways to Gamify Your Tasks and Get Work Done Faster</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/5-ways-to-gamify-your-tasks-and-get-work-done-faster/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>I used to think gaming was an absolute waste of time. Even though I’ve spent over half a year in total playing World of Warcraft over the past 10 years, I would sometimes feel guilty ‘wasting’ all that time. But luckily, after a little bit of research, I realised that there are actually a number [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/productivity/5-ways-to-gamify-your-tasks-and-get-work-done-faster/">5 Ways to Gamify Your Tasks and Get Work Done Faster</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 14:00:24 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>