<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Blog on Tailscale</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/xavwe/rss-aggregator/refs/heads/main/feeds/blog-on-tailscale-019cfa8d.xml</link><description>Archived feed from https://tailscale.com/blog/index.xml</description><item><title>Stream Tailscale logs to Google Cloud Storage</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/gcs-log-streaming</link><description><![CDATA[Send Tailscale logs directly into your own GCS storage and manage them with your existing Google Cloud controls.]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fleet device posture integration is now generally available</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/fleet-device-posture-integration</link><description><![CDATA[Use Fleet-managed device state in Tailscale access policies to ensure access matches device posture.]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 15:15:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Huntress device posture integration is now generally available</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/huntress-device-posture-integration</link><description><![CDATA[As Huntress endpoint protection posture changes, access policies can respond automatically—without manual updates.]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tailscale Peer Relays is now generally available</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/peer-relays-ga</link><description><![CDATA[Customer-deployed, high-throughput relaying with production-level readiness, and you can run on it on any Tailscale node.]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 14:45:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Aperture: Stop choosing between safe AI and fast AI</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/aperture-partners-update</link><description><![CDATA[Aperture is an AI gateway inside your network, one that takes the friction out of deploying AI for your organization.]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 13:45:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Built for momentum: Tailscale Winter Update Week</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/winter-update-week-26</link><description><![CDATA[It’s Winter Update Week: five days of shipping, sharing, and showing where secure connectivity is headed next.]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Staying secure and simple in a complex world</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/welcome-ross-kukulinski</link><description><![CDATA[Ross is joining to help us shape what Tailscale's product lines become next, as we grow and evolve. We're going to keep it understandable, predictable, and boring in all the right ways.]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 3 Feb 2026 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A first look at Aperture by Tailscale (private alpha)</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/aperture-private-alpha</link><description><![CDATA[We built an AI gateway that provides security and visibility for coding agent usage across organizations, to make the safe way of accessing AI the easy way.]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Tailscale Peer Relays saved my holiday: a 12.5X performance boost from India</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/peer-relays-international-networks</link><description><![CDATA[Visiting family in India used to mean sluggish, inconsistent connections to a U.S. homelab. Tailscale Peer Relays meant no more frozen terminals or slow transfers.]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 16:30:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>This month at Tailscale for January 2026</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/january-26-product-update</link><description><![CDATA[What's new in Tailscale clients this month, including changes to containers, workload identity federation, and our GitHub Action.]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tailscale + BlueBubbles puts iMessage on Windows, Android, or anywhere</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/bluebubbles-tailscale-imessage-android-pc-no-port-forwarding</link><description><![CDATA[BlueBubbles is a clever way to bring iMessage to almost any device. Tailscale makes it far more simple to hook it all up.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hypergrowth isn&apos;t always easy</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/hypergrowth-isnt-always-easy</link><description><![CDATA[We don't get enough chances to talk about system architecture. So let's talk about outages, performance, coordination servers, and continuous improvement.]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tailscale the Terraform way</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/open-source-terraform-module</link><description><![CDATA[Our customers had a reasonable request: "Make the VM come up already connected to my tailnet." So we built this module for them.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mendix Cloud Private Connectivity powered by Tailscale now available in public beta</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/mendix-cloud-private-connectivity-beta</link><description><![CDATA[Mendix customers can now create private, secure connections between their Mendix Cloud apps and their own infrastructure—without the hassle of complex networking set ups and arduous security reviews.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 8 Jan 2026 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>This month at Tailscale for December 2025</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/december-25-product-update</link><description><![CDATA[What's new in Tailscale clients this month, including a number of fixes, changes, and updates to our latest features.]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>