<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Blog on Tailscale</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/xavwe/rss-aggregator/refs/heads/main/feeds/blog-on-tailscale-019cfa8d.xml</link><description>Archived feed from https://tailscale.com/blog/index.xml</description><item><title>A first look at Aperture by Tailscale (private alpha)</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/aperture-private-alpha</link><description><![CDATA[We built an AI gateway that provides security and visibility for coding agent usage across organizations, to make the safe way of accessing AI the easy way.]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Tailscale Peer Relays saved my holiday: a 12.5X performance boost from India</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/peer-relays-international-networks</link><description><![CDATA[Visiting family in India used to mean sluggish, inconsistent connections to a U.S. homelab. Tailscale Peer Relays meant no more frozen terminals or slow transfers.]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 16:30:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>This month at Tailscale for January 2026</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/january-26-product-update</link><description><![CDATA[What's new in Tailscale clients this month, including changes to containers, workload identity federation, and our GitHub Action.]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tailscale + BlueBubbles puts iMessage on Windows, Android, or anywhere</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/bluebubbles-tailscale-imessage-android-pc-no-port-forwarding</link><description><![CDATA[BlueBubbles is a clever way to bring iMessage to almost any device. Tailscale makes it far more simple to hook it all up.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hypergrowth isn&apos;t always easy</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/hypergrowth-isnt-always-easy</link><description><![CDATA[We don't get enough chances to talk about system architecture. So let's talk about outages, performance, coordination servers, and continuous improvement.]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tailscale the Terraform way</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/open-source-terraform-module</link><description><![CDATA[Our customers had a reasonable request: "Make the VM come up already connected to my tailnet." So we built this module for them.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mendix Cloud Private Connectivity powered by Tailscale now available in public beta</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/mendix-cloud-private-connectivity-beta</link><description><![CDATA[Mendix customers can now create private, secure connections between their Mendix Cloud apps and their own infrastructure—without the hassle of complex networking set ups and arduous security reviews.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 8 Jan 2026 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>This month at Tailscale for December 2025</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/december-25-product-update</link><description><![CDATA[What's new in Tailscale clients this month, including a number of fixes, changes, and updates to our latest features.]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Blacksmith used Tailscale Services to work around ISP degradation</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/blacksmith-tailscale-services-isp-degradation</link><description><![CDATA[TL;DR: We built a transparent proxy that routes GitHub traffic through an alternate network path with direct GitHub peering, giving our runners defence-in-depth against ISP routing failures. No code changes required for customers—GitHub Actions interact with GitHub exactly as they used to. This proxy uses the newly announced Tailscale Services for secure load balancing and Squid for high-performance proxying and caching.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Chat-tails: Throwback terminal chat, built on Tailscale</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/chat-tails-terminal-chat</link><description><![CDATA[You can do a lot, building on top of Tailscale. But you can also do much less, intentionally. Here's one example.]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 21:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Let&apos;s put Tailscale on a jailbroken Kindle</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/tailscale-jailbroken-kindle</link><description><![CDATA[Add easier SSH, Taildrop, and secure connectivity to a Kindle that's ready to do much more.]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 1 Dec 2025 17:30:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>50,000 subscribers (and endless thanks)</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/50k-youtube-subscribers</link><description><![CDATA[Thanks to our viewers, we can make the kinds of videos we want: useful and interesting explainers and resources, with an emphasis on community feedback.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tailscale GitHub Action v4: faster, more reliable, and new features</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/github-action-v4</link><description><![CDATA[This rewrite opens doors to new functionality and provides a drastically improved and smoother CI/CD experience.]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 17:00:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why you should mail your parents a Tailscale node</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/exit-node-parents-streaming-support</link><description><![CDATA[Set up a VPN, remote tech support, file sharing, and other useful things by mailing a little Tailscale to your friends and family.]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 4 Nov 2025 14:15:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>This month at Tailscale: Fall Updates, GitHub Actions, and Tailnet name types</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/october-25-product-update</link><description><![CDATA[What's new in Tailscale clients this month, including a new GitHub Action, Peer Relays, Services, and more]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 21:00:45 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>