<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Blog on Tailscale</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/xavwe/rss-aggregator/refs/heads/main/feeds/blog-on-tailscale-019cfa8d.xml</link><description>Archived feed from https://tailscale.com/blog/index.xml</description><item><title>This month at Tailscale for December 2025</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/december-25-product-update</link><description><![CDATA[What's new in Tailscale clients this month, including a number of fixes, changes, and updates to our latest features.]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Blacksmith used Tailscale Services to work around ISP degradation</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/blacksmith-tailscale-services-isp-degradation</link><description><![CDATA[TL;DR: We built a transparent proxy that routes GitHub traffic through an alternate network path with direct GitHub peering, giving our runners defence-in-depth against ISP routing failures. No code changes required for customers—GitHub Actions interact with GitHub exactly as they used to. This proxy uses the newly announced Tailscale Services for secure load balancing and Squid for high-performance proxying and caching.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Chat-tails: Throwback terminal chat, built on Tailscale</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/chat-tails-terminal-chat</link><description><![CDATA[You can do a lot, building on top of Tailscale. But you can also do much less, intentionally. Here's one example.]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 21:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Let&apos;s put Tailscale on a jailbroken Kindle</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/tailscale-jailbroken-kindle</link><description><![CDATA[Add easier SSH, Taildrop, and secure connectivity to a Kindle that's ready to do much more.]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 1 Dec 2025 17:30:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>50,000 subscribers (and endless thanks)</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/50k-youtube-subscribers</link><description><![CDATA[Thanks to our viewers, we can make the kinds of videos we want: useful and interesting explainers and resources, with an emphasis on community feedback.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tailscale GitHub Action v4: faster, more reliable, and new features</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/github-action-v4</link><description><![CDATA[This rewrite opens doors to new functionality and provides a drastically improved and smoother CI/CD experience.]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 17:00:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why you should mail your parents a Tailscale node</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/exit-node-parents-streaming-support</link><description><![CDATA[Set up a VPN, remote tech support, file sharing, and other useful things by mailing a little Tailscale to your friends and family.]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 4 Nov 2025 14:15:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>This month at Tailscale: Fall Updates, GitHub Actions, and Tailnet name types</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/october-25-product-update</link><description><![CDATA[What's new in Tailscale clients this month, including a new GitHub Action, Peer Relays, Services, and more]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 21:00:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A recap of Tailscale&apos;s Fall Update Week</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/fall-update-week-25-wrap</link><description><![CDATA[Fall Update Week is nearing its end, and Tailscale is a different product at its finish. As we said at the outset: simpler, smarter, and more connected.]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Building on Tailscale: How we made a tiny identity provider</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/building-tsidp</link><description><![CDATA[How to quickly build and configure secure apps that work inside and outside a tailnet.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Better authentication with workload identity federation</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/workload-identity-beta</link><description><![CDATA[Today we’re excited to announce workload identity federation, a better way for your infrastructure and CI/CD systems to securely authenticate to Tailscale without managing long-lived API keys, auth keys, or OAuth clients.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>App capabilities, now for all your apps</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/app-capabilities</link><description><![CDATA[Tailscale’s identity-based access controls allow for building powerful, secure applications on entirely private tailnets. You can already leverage user identity with our Go-based tsnet. Now we’re building on our prior work and taking it a significant step further, with Tailscale app capabilities. With the latest version of Tailscale’s serve function, third-party applications can accept grants through standard HTTP headers, in whatever language suits your needs.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Introducing Tailscale Peer Relays</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/peer-relays-beta</link><description><![CDATA[Tailscale Peer Relays provides a customer-deployed and managed traffic relaying mechanism. By advertising itself as a peer relay, a Tailscale node can relay traffic for any peer nodes on the tailnet, even for traffic bound to itself. Tailscale Peer Relays can only relay traffic for nodes on your tailnet, and only for nodes that have access to the peer relay. Because they’re managed entirely by the customer, peer relays are less throughput-constrained than Tailscale’s managed DERP relays, and can provide higher throughput connections for traffic to and from locked-down cloud infrastructure, or behind strict network firewalls.]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 14:15:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>One organization, multiple tailnets</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/multiple-tailnets-alpha</link><description><![CDATA[We’re adding something new to Tailscale: organizations can now create and manage more than one tailnet, all backed by the same identity provider.]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Visual policy editor is now generally available</title><link>https://tailscale.com/blog/visual-editor-ga</link><description><![CDATA[Tailscale’s visual policy editor provides a graphical view of your tailnet policies, while staying in harmony with a traditional JSON file.]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>