<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jeff Geerling</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/xavwe/rss-aggregator/refs/heads/main/feeds/jeff-geerling-4377cb53.xml</link><description>Archived feed from https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog.xml</description><item><title>Exploring a Modern SMPTE 2110 Broadcast Truck With My Dad</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/exploring-a-modern-smpte-2110-broadcast-truck-with-my-dad/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>In October, my Dad and I got to go behind the scenes at two St. Louis Blues (NHL hockey) games, and observe the massive team effort involved in putting together a modern digital sports broadcast.</p>
<figure class="insert-image"><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/exploring-a-modern-smpte-2110-broadcast-truck-with-my-dad/blues-game-production-truck-prod-room.jpg"
 alt="Broadcast production room in 45 Flex truck at a Blues game" width="700" height="auto">
</figure>

<p>I wanted to explore the timing and digital side of a modern <a href="https://www.smpte.org/standards/st2110">SMPTE 2110</a> mobile unit, and my Dad has been involved in studio and live broadcast for decades, so he enjoyed the experience as the engineer <em>not</em> on duty!</p>]]></description><pubDate>Sat, 7 Feb 2026 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The first good Raspberry Pi Laptop</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/the-first-good-raspberry-pi-laptop/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Ever since the <a href="https://www.raspberrypi.com/products/compute-module-5/">Raspberry Pi Compute Module 5</a> was introduced, I wondered why nobody built a decent laptop chassis around it.</p>
<figure class="insert-image"><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/the-first-good-raspberry-pi-laptop/argon-one-up-laptop-hero-raspberry-pi-mug.jpg"
 alt="Argon ONE UP laptop with Raspberry Pi mug on desk" width="700" height="auto">
</figure>

<p>You could swap out a low spec CM5 for a higher spec, and get an instant computer upgrade. Or, assuming a CM6 comes out someday in the same form factor, the laptop chassis could get an entirely new life with that upgrade.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 6 Feb 2026 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ode to the AA Battery</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/ode-to-the-aa-battery/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Recently <a href="https://x.com/Merocle/status/2015496917472489751">this post from @Merocle</a> caught my eye:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I'm fixing my iFixit soldering station. I haven't used it for a long time and the battery has gone overdischarge. I hope it will come back to life. Unfortunately, there are no replacements available for sale at the moment.</p>
</blockquote>
<figure class="insert-image"><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/ode-to-the-aa-battery/ifixit-soldering-usb-battery-merocle-torn-down.jpg"
 alt="iFixit soldering hub torn down - used with permission" width="500" height="auto">
</figure>

<p>Devices with built-in rechargeable batteries have been bugging me a lot lately. It's convenient to have a device you can take with you and use anywhere. And with modern Li-ion cells, battery life is remarkable.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Recapping My 5 Year Old Studio Monitors</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/recapping-my-5-year-old-studio-monitors/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, I started hearing a slight crackle at the loudest parts of whenever sound was playing through my <a href="https://amzn.to/3LVd3DY">PreSonus Eris E3.5 speakers</a>. It was <em>very</em> faint, but quite annoying, especially when editing my YouTube videos.</p>
<figure class="insert-image"><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/recapping-my-5-year-old-studio-monitors/presonus-eris-e35-speakers.jpeg"
 alt="PreSonus Eris E3.5 speakers on workbench" width="700" height="auto">
</figure>

<p>For a few days I thought it could be a hearing problem (at this point in my life, every year brings a new health adventure...), but after testing my wired headphones and another small computer speaker on the same output, I determined the problem was, indeed, coming from the PreSonus speakers.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 23:05:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Migrating 13,000 Comments from Drupal to Hugo</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/migrating-13000-comments-from-drupal-to-hugo/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>After 16 years on the LAMP stack, I finished <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/migrated-to-hugo/">migrating this website from Drupal to Hugo</a> a few weeks ago.</p>
<p>What's old is new, as this blog was <em>originally</em> built with <a href="https://github.com/hyphanet/Thingamablog-Freenet">Thingamablog</a>, a Java-based Static Site Generator (SSG) I ran on my Mac to generate HTML and FTP it up to my first webserver (over 20 years ago!).</p>
<p>The main reason I moved from an SSG to Drupal was to add <em>comments</em>. I wanted my blog to have the same level of interactivity I had pre-Thingamablog, when I was (briefly) on Xanga.com.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 02:43:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Raspberry Pi&apos;s new AI HAT adds 8GB of RAM for local LLMs</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/raspberry-pi-ai-hat-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<figure class="insert-image"><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/raspberry-pi-ai-hat-2/raspberry-pi-ai-hat-2.jpg"
 alt="Raspberry Pi AI HAT&#43; 2" width="700" height="auto">
</figure>

<p>Today Raspberry Pi launched their new <a href="https://www.raspberrypi.com/products/ai-hat-plus-2/">$130 AI HAT+ 2</a> which includes a Hailo 10H and 8 GB of <a href="https://www.micron.com/products/memory/dram-components/lpddr4/part-catalog/part-detail/mt53e2g32d4de-046-wt-c">LPDDR4X RAM</a>.</p>
<p>With that, the Hailo 10H is capable of running LLMs entirely standalone, freeing the Pi's CPU and system RAM for other tasks. The chip runs at a maximum of 3W, with 40 TOPS of INT8 NPU inference performance in addition to the equivalent 26 TOPS INT4 machine vision performance on the earlier AI HAT with Hailo 8.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Raspberry Pi Pico Mini Rack GPS Clock</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/pico-gps-clock-mini-rack/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>I wanted to have the most accurate timepiece possible mounted in my mini rack. Therefore I built this:</p>
<figure class="insert-image"><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/pico-gps-clock-mini-rack/pico-gps-clock-mini-rack.jpg"
 alt="Raspberry Pi Pico GPS Clock for Mini Rack" width="700" height="auto">
</figure>

<p>This is a GPS-based clock running on a Raspberry Pi Pico in a custom 1U 10&quot; rack faceplate. The clock displays time based on a GPS input, and will not display time until a GPS timing lock has been acquired.</p>
<ul>
<li>When you turn on the Pico, the display reads <code>----</code></li>
<li>Upon 3D fix, you get a time on the clock, and the colon starts blinking</li>
<li>If the 3D fix is lost, the colon goes solid</li>
<li>When the 3D fix is regained, the colon starts blinking again</li>
</ul>
<p>For full details on designing and building this clock, see:</p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Local Email Debugging with Mailpit</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/mailpit-local-email-debugging/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>For the past decade, I've used <a href="https://github.com/mailhog/MailHog">Mailhog</a> for local email debugging. Besides working on web applications that deal with email, I've long used email as the primary notification system for comments on the blog.</p>
<p>I built an <a href="https://github.com/geerlingguy/ansible-role-mailhog">Ansible role for Mailhog</a>, and it was one of the main features of <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2015/major-improvements-drupal-vm/">Drupal VM</a>, a popular local development environment for Drupal I sunset 3 years ago.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, barring any future updates from the maintainers, it seems like <a href="https://github.com/mailhog/MailHog/issues/466">Mailhog has not been maintained</a> for four years now. It still <em>works</em>, but something as complex as an email debugging environment needs ongoing maintenance to stay relevant.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 9 Jan 2026 03:30:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Raspberry Pi is cheaper than a Mini PC again (that&apos;s not good)</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/raspberry-pi-cheaper-than-mini-pc/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Almost a year ago, I found that <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/intel-n100-better-value-raspberry-pi/">N100 Mini PCs were cheaper than a decked-out Raspberry Pi 5</a>. So comparing systems with:</p>
<ul>
<li>16GB of RAM</li>
<li>512GB NVMe SSD</li>
<li>Including case, cooler, and power adapter</li>
</ul>
<p>Back in March last year, a GMKtec Mini PC was $159, and a similar-spec Pi 5 was $208.</p>
<p>Today? The <a href="https://amzn.to/4srcKB3">same GMKtec Mini PC</a> is $246.99, and the same Pi 5 is $246.95:</p>
<figure class="insert-image"><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/raspberry-pi-cheaper-than-mini-pc/costs-gmktec-vs-pi-5.jpg"
 alt="GMKtec N100 Mini PC vs Pi 5 16GB pricing 2025" width="700" height="auto">
</figure>

<p>Today, because of the wonderful RAM shortages<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, the Mini PC is the same price as a fully kitted-out Raspberry Pi 5.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 5 Jan 2026 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>JeffGeerling.com has been Migrated to Hugo</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/migrated-to-hugo/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Since 2009, this website has <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2009/moved-drupal-hello-drupal">run on Drupal</a>. Starting with Drupal 6, and progressing through major site upgrades and migrations to 7, 8, 9, and 10, I used the site as a way to dogfood the same CMS (Content Management System) I used in my day job for <em>over a decade</em>.</p>
<figure class="insert-image"><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/migrated-to-hugo/jeffgeerling-old-drupal.png"
 alt="JeffGeerling.com - Old Drupal site" width="700" height="auto">
</figure>

<p>But as time progressed—especially after completing a <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2020/migrating-jeffgeerlingcom-drupal-8-live">grueling upgrade from Drupal 7 to 8</a>—my enthusiasm for maintaining what's now a more enterprise-focused <a href="https://www.acquia.com/blog/what-digital-experience-platform-dxp">Digital Experience Platform</a> or 'DXP' for a personal blog has waned.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Sat, 3 Jan 2026 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Testing the Mono Gateway, a custom-built 10 Gbps Router</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/testing-mono-gateway-custom-built-10-gbps-router/</link><description><![CDATA[<figure class="insert-image"><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2026/testing-mono-gateway-custom-built-10-gbps-router/mono-gateway-router-hero.jpeg"
 alt="Mono Gateway" width="700" height="auto">
</figure>

<p>Last month, the stars aligned for me to bring the <a href="https://mono.si">Mono Gateway</a> (a 10 Gbps router that YouTuber <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@tomazzaman">Tomaž Zaman</a> and his team at Mono built from scratch) on a trip to Phoenix, and test it with one of the most OP network test boxes I've ever seen, at the <a href="https://www.servethehome.com">ServeTheHome</a> HQ.</p>
<p>In this video, Patrick (from STH) and I put Gateway through a real-world torture test using CyPerf:</p>
<div class="yt-embed">
<style>.embed-container { position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden; max-width: 100%; } .embed-container iframe, .embed-container object, .embed-container embed { position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; }</style><div class='embed-container'><iframe src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/3D5q3NWEMZY' frameborder='0' allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div>
<h2 id="mono-gateway">Mono Gateway</h2>
<p>The Gateway is a small (1U/desktop) router with features like a 4-core Arm CPU, 8GB of ECC LPDDR RAM, and decent expansion options for a compact router.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 2 Jan 2026 15:12:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Dell&apos;s version of the DGX Spark fixes pain points</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/dells-version-dgx-spark-fixes-pain-points/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Dell sent me two of their GB10 mini workstations to test:</p>
<figure class="insert-image"><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/dells-version-dgx-spark-fixes-pain-points/dell-pro-max-gb10-two.jpeg"
 alt="Dell Pro Max with GB10" width="700" height="394">
</figure>

<p>In this blog post, I'll cover the base system, just one of the two nodes. Cluster testing is ongoing, and I'll cover things like AI model training and networking more in depth next year, likely with comparisons to the <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/i-clustered-four-framework-mainboards-test-huge-llms">Framework Desktop cluster</a> and <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/15-tb-vram-on-mac-studio-rdma-over-thunderbolt-5">Mac Studio cluster</a> I've also been testing.</p>
<p>But many of the same caveats of the DGX Spark (namely, price to performance is not great if you just want to run LLMs on a small desktop) apply to Dell's GB10 box as well.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 15:00:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>NIST was 5 μs off UTC after last week&apos;s power cut</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/nist-was-5-%CE%BCs-utc-after-last-weeks-power-cut/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>If you were 5 microseconds late today, blame it on NIST.</p>
<p>Their facility in Boulder Colorado just had its power cut for multiple days. After a backup generator failed, their main ensemble clock lost track of UTC, or Universal Time Coordinated.</p>
<p>But even if you used the <a href="https://tf.nist.gov/tf-cgi/servers.cgi">NTP timing servers they run</a>, they were never off by more than 5 microseconds.</p>
<p>5 μs might seem insignificant. But it <em>is</em> significant for scientists and universities who rely on NIST's more <a href="https://wsts.atis.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/04-Judah-Levine.The-NIST-Fiber-Based-Time-Service.pdf">specialized timing signals</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 16:28:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Big GPUs don&apos;t need big PCs</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/big-gpus-dont-need-big-pcs/</link><description><![CDATA[<figure class="insert-image"><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/big-gpus-dont-need-big-pcs/raspberry-pi-egpu-vs-pc-gpu-setup.jpeg"
 alt="Raspberry Pi eGPU vs PC GPU" width="700" height="394">
</figure>

<p>Ever since I got <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/using-amd-gpus-on-raspberry-pi-without-recompiling-linux">AMD</a>, <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/all-intel-gpus-run-on-raspberry-pi-and-risc-v">Intel</a>, and <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/nvidia-graphics-cards-work-on-pi-5-and-rockchip">Nvidia</a> graphics cards to run on a Raspberry Pi, I had a nagging question:</p>
<p><em>What's the point?</em></p>
<p>The Raspberry Pi only has 1 lane of PCIe Gen 3 bandwidth available for a connection to an eGPU. That's not much. Especially considering a modern desktop has at least one slot with 16 lanes of PCIe Gen 5 bandwidth. That's 8 GT/s versus 512 GT/s. Not a fair fight.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2025 15:04:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>1.5 TB of VRAM on Mac Studio - RDMA over Thunderbolt 5</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/15-tb-vram-on-mac-studio-rdma-over-thunderbolt-5/</link><description><![CDATA[<figure class="insert-image"><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/15-tb-vram-on-mac-studio-rdma-over-thunderbolt-5/mac-studio-cluster-1-hero.jpg"
 alt="Mac Studio Cluster" width="700" height="394">
</figure>

<p>Apple gave me access to this Mac Studio cluster to test RDMA over Thunderbolt, a <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/macos-release-notes/macos-26_2-release-notes#RDMA-over-Thunderbolt">new feature in macOS 26.2</a>. The easiest way to test it is with <a href="https://exolabs.net">Exo 1.0</a>, an open source private AI clustering tool. RDMA lets the Macs all act like they have one giant pool of RAM, which speeds up things like massive AI models.</p>
<p>The stack of Macs I tested, with 1.5 TB of unified memory, costs just shy of $40,000, and if you're wondering, no I cannot justify spending that much money for this. Apple loaned the Mac Studios for testing. I also have to thank DeskPi for sending over the 4-post mini rack containing the cluster.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 14:00:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>CM0 - a new Raspberry Pi you can&apos;t buy</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/cm0-new-raspberry-pi-you-cant-buy/</link><description><![CDATA[<figure class="insert-image"><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/cm0-new-raspberry-pi-you-cant-buy/raspberry-pi-cm0.jpeg"
 alt="Raspberry Pi CM0" width="700" height="394">
</figure>

<p>This little postage stamp is actually a full Raspberry Pi Zero 2, complete with eMMC storage and WiFi.</p>
<p>But you can't get one. Well, not unless you buy the <a href="https://edatec.cn/docs/cm0nano/ds/">CM0NANO development board from EDAtec</a>, or you live in China.</p>
<p>This little guy doesn't have an HDMI port, Ethernet, or even USB. It's a special version of the 'Compute Module' line of boards. Little Raspberry Pi 'System on Modules' (SoMs), they're called.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 15:10:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Benchmarking NVENC video transcoding on the Pi</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/benchmarking-nvenc-video-transcoding-on-pi/</link><description><![CDATA[<figure class="insert-image"><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/benchmarking-nvenc-video-transcoding-on-pi/asus-proart-egpu-dock-4070-ti-raspberry-pi.jpg"
 alt="ASUS ProArt 4070 Ti in eGPU dock on Raspberry Pi CM5" width="700" height="394">
</figure>

<p>Now that <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/nvidia-graphics-cards-work-on-pi-5-and-rockchip">Nvidia GPUs run on the Raspberry Pi</a>, I've been putting all the ones I own through their paces.</p>
<p>Many people have an older Nvidia card (like a 3060) laying around from an upgrade. So could a Pi be suitable for GPU-accelerated video transcoding, either standalone for conversion, or running something like Jellyfin for video library management and streaming?</p>
<p>That's what I set out to do, and the first step, besides getting the drivers and CUDA going (see blog post linked above), was to find a way to get a repeatable benchmark going.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 22:06:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The DC-ROMA II is the fastest RISC-V laptop and is odd</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/dc-roma-ii-fastest-risc-v-laptop-and-odd/</link><description><![CDATA[<figure class="insert-image"><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/dc-roma-ii-fastest-risc-v-laptop-and-odd/dc-roma-ii-framework-external-display.jpeg"
 alt="Framework 13 DC-ROMA II DeepComputing Laptop with external HDMI display" width="700" height="394">
</figure>

<p>Inside this <a href="https://frame.work/laptop13">Framework 13</a> laptop is a special mainboard developed by DeepComputing in collaboration with Framework. It has an 8-core RISC-V processor, the ESWIN 7702X—not your typical AMD, Intel, or even <em>Arm</em> SoC. The full laptop version I tested <a href="https://store.deepcomputing.io/products/dc-roma-ai-pc-risc-v-mainboard-ii-for-framework-laptop-13?variant=50950609895588">costs $1119</a> and gets you about the performance of a Raspberry Pi.</p>
<p>A Pi 4—the one that came out in 2019.</p>
<p>But unlike the Pi 4, this eats up 25 watts of power at idle, meaning the poor battery only lasts 2-3 hours.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 8 Dec 2025 15:40:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The RAM Shortage Comes for Us All</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/ram-shortage-comes-us-all/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Memory price inflation comes for us all, and if you're not affected yet, just wait.</p>
<p>I was building a new PC last month using some parts I had bought earlier this year. The 64 Gigabyte T-Create DDR5 memory kit I used cost $209 then. Today? The <a href="https://www.microcenter.com/product/680461/teamgroup-t-create-expert-64gb-(2-x-32gb)-ddr5-6400-pc5-51200-cl34-dual-channel-desktop-memory-kit-ctced564g6400hc34bdc01-black">same kit costs $650</a>!</p>
<p>Just in the past week, we found out <a href="https://www.raspberrypi.com/news/1gb-raspberry-pi-5-now-available-at-45-and-memory-driven-price-rises/">Raspberry Pi's increasing their single board computer prices</a>. Micron's <a href="https://investors.micron.com/news-releases/news-release-details/micron-announces-exit-crucial-consumer-business">killing the Crucial brand of RAM and storage devices <em>completely</em></a>, meaning there's gonna be one fewer consumer memory manufacturer. <a href="https://www.pcworld.com/article/2998935/ram-is-so-expensive-samsung-wont-even-sell-it-to-samsung.html"><em>Samsung</em> can't even buy RAM from themselves</a> to build their own Smartphones, and small vendors like <a href="https://x.com/librecomputer/status/1995592912063922578">Libre Computer</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AyueVGLT7qI">Mono</a> are seeing RAM prices double, triple, or even <em>worse</em>, and they're not even buying the latest RAM tech!</p>]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 4 Dec 2025 18:43:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why doesn&apos;t Apple make a standalone Touch ID?</title><link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/why-doesnt-apple-make-standalone-touch-id/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>I finally upgraded to a mechanical keyboard. But because Apple's so protective of their Touch ID hardware, there aren't any mechanical keyboards with that feature built in.</p>
<figure class="insert-image"><img src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2025/why-doesnt-apple-make-standalone-touch-id/apple-touch-id-external-3d-printed-sensor.jpg"
 alt="Apple Touch ID - external 3D printed sensor" width="700" height="394">
</figure>

<p>But there <em>is</em> a way to hack it. It's incredibly wasteful, and takes a bit more patience than I think <em>most</em> people have, but you basically take an Apple Magic Keyboard with Touch ID, rip out the Touch ID, and install it in a 3D printed box, along with the keyboard's logic board.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 3 Dec 2025 22:38:04 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>