<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>LifeNotes | Ali Abdaal</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/xavwe/rss-aggregator/refs/heads/main/feeds/lifenotes-ali-abdaal-d80cb5c2.xml</link><description>Archived feed from https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/feed/</description><item><title>My biggest mistake with goal-setting…</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/my-biggest-mistake-with-goal-setting/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>A couple weeks ago, I was&#160;interviewed&#160;on my friend and former coach Corey’s podcast. One topic we talked about was the backstory behind why and how I decided to build an&#160;online business school&#160;this year. One interesting tidbit (or so listeners to that episode tell me) was that I kept the project a secret from my team [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/my-biggest-mistake-with-goal-setting/">My biggest mistake with goal-setting&#8230;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What’s the point of goals?</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/whats-the-point-of-goals/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Last week we hosted Spark 2026, our free annual workshop where me and some guest speakers walked participants through reflecting on 2025, figuring out where there life’s going, and setting goals for 2026. Big thank you to everyone who attended: I had a great time running it, and I hope you got some value out [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/whats-the-point-of-goals/">What’s the point of goals?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 9 Jan 2026 12:27:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>I felt bad at midnight last night…</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/i-felt-bad-at-midnight-last-night/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>while I was lying in bed last night, I made the mistake of clicking on a notification from Twitter/X. Can’t remember what it was, but it was intriguing and I clicked on it. And then without realising it, I found myself scrolling the feed for over an hour. And it wasn’t just that I was [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/i-felt-bad-at-midnight-last-night/">I felt bad at midnight last night…</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 2 Jan 2026 12:25:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>On measuring how much freedom you have…</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/on-measuring-how-much-freedom-you-have/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>This week I wanted to write about an idea I’ve been noodling on for a few weeks: around Freedom and what that means and how to quantify it. I’ve long known that “freedom” is one of my core values—maybe even the top one. I’m not entirely sure why. When I’ve done those exercises about identifying [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/on-measuring-how-much-freedom-you-have/">On measuring how much freedom you have&#8230;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 12:03:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The rusty tap theory that changed my creativity</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/the-rusty-tap-theory-that-changed-my-creativity/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>I wanted to share some good news this week &#8211; this has been my biggest week in terms of creative output in… I don’t know how long. I feel like I’ve had so many ideas (including some good ones), and come up with a lot of stuff that I genuinely want to share with you [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/the-rusty-tap-theory-that-changed-my-creativity/">The rusty tap theory that changed my creativity</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A reminder about time management…</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/a-reminder-about-time-management/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>I wanted to tell you about a moment that happened this morning that I’m highly proud of. I’ve just gotten back to Hong Kong from LA where I spent a week attending an event hosted by&#160;Taki Moore, aimed at 7-figure-and-above online coach type people, which I guess I fall into the category of. Amazing experience [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/a-reminder-about-time-management/">A reminder about time management&#8230;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Sun, 9 Nov 2025 11:58:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>3 Reminders to Myself…</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/3-reminders-to-myself/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>I’m back in Hong Kong this week after a nice team off-site in Bali where the 14 of us hung out in a lovely villa, did some business planning stuff, did some excursions and dinners etc. Great vibes all round. Except on the last day, where I got struck with food poisoning and ended up [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/3-reminders-to-myself/">3 Reminders to Myself&#8230;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2025 11:56:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Is your intuition smarter than your spreadsheets?</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/is-your-intuition-smarter-than-your-spreadsheets/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>You might’ve noticed (actually tbh you probably haven’t lol) that I haven’t sent an issue of this newsletter in a few weeks. In August I was visiting London with Izzy and our baby, and decided to take a break from “content stuff” to be able to hang with family and friends without the “pressure” of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/is-your-intuition-smarter-than-your-spreadsheets/">Is your intuition smarter than your spreadsheets?</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 8 Sep 2025 11:54:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Good Student vs The Good Entrepreneur</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/the-good-student-vs-the-good-entrepreneur/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>A few days ago, we kicked off the $1K Challenge that I’ve been mentioning here and on socials for the past few weeks. We’ve got 1,300 people from 100+ countries taking part, all working towards making their first $1,000 online. But more importantly, they’re here to learn the key skills of independent income generation that’ll [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/the-good-student-vs-the-good-entrepreneur/">The Good Student vs The Good Entrepreneur</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 6 Aug 2025 11:53:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Locking In…</title><link>https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/locking-in/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>It’s been a pretty rammed week &#8211; I’ve been “locked-in” (as they say) from like 8am to 11pm all day everyday working on curriculum content for our $1k Challenge starting in a few days. We’ve got nearly 1,000 people from all over the world joining, all aiming to build a business that makes at least $1,000 in [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://aliabdaal.com/newsletter/locking-in/">Locking In&#8230;</a> appeared first on <a href="https://aliabdaal.com">Ali Abdaal</a>.</p>]]></description><pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2025 11:50:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>