<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Simon Willison&apos;s Weblog</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/xavwe/rss-aggregator/refs/heads/main/feeds/simon-willison-s-weblog-2b081550.xml</link><description>Archived feed from https://simonwillison.net/atom/everything</description><item><title>Quoting James Luan</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/8/james-luan/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<blockquote cite="https://zilliz.com/blog/will-amazon-s3-vectors-kill-vector-databases-or-save-them"><p>I recently spoke with the CTO of a popular AI note-taking app who told me something surprising: they spend <strong><em>twice</em></strong> <em>as much</em> on vector search as they do on OpenAI API calls. Think about that for a second. Running the retrieval layer costs them more than paying for the LLM itself.</p></blockquote>
<p class="cite">&mdash; <a href="https://zilliz.com/blog/will-amazon-s3-vectors-kill-vector-databases-or-save-them">James Luan</a>, Engineering architect of Milvus</p>

    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/vector-search">vector-search</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/embeddings">embeddings</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 8 Sep 2025 16:24:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Is the LLM response wrong, or have you just failed to iterate it?</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/7/is-the-llm-response-wrong-or-have-you-just-failed-to-iterate-it/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://mikecaulfield.substack.com/p/is-the-llm-response-wrong-or-have">Is the LLM response wrong, or have you just failed to iterate it?</a></strong></p>
More from Mike Caulfield (see also <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/7/the-sift-method/">the SIFT method</a>). He starts with a <em>fantastic</em> example of Google's <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/7/ai-mode/">AI mode</a> usually correctly handling a common piece of misinformation but occasionally falling for it (the curse of non-deterministic systems), then shows an example if what he calls a "sorting prompt" as a follow-up:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What is the evidence for and against this being a real photo of Shirley Slade?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The response starts with a non-committal "there is compelling evidence for and against...", then by the end has firmly convinced itself that the photo is indeed a fake. It reads like a fact-checking variant of "think step by step".</p>
<p>Mike neatly describes a problem I've also observed recently where "hallucination" is frequently mis-applied as meaning any time a model makes a mistake:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The term hallucination has become nearly worthless in the LLM discourse. It initially described a very weird, mostly non-humanlike behavior where LLMs would make up things out of whole cloth that did not seem to exist as claims referenced any known source material or claims inferable from any known source material. Hallucinations as stuff made up out of nothing. Subsequently people began calling any error or imperfect summary a hallucination, rendering the term worthless.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In this example is the initial incorrect answers were not hallucinations: they correctly summarized online content that contained misinformation. The trick then is to encourage the model to look further, using "sorting prompts" like these:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Facts and misconceptions and hype about what I posted</li>
<li>What is the evidence for and against the claim I posted</li>
<li>Look at the most recent information on this issue, summarize how it shifts the analysis (if at all), and provide link to the latest info</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>I appreciated this closing footnote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Should platforms have more features to nudge users to this sort of iteration? Yes. They should. Getting people to iterate investigation rather than argue with LLMs would be a good first step out of this mess that the chatbot model has created.</p>
</blockquote>

    <p><small></small>Via <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/mikecaulfield.bsky.social/post/3lya2nv7xi226">@mikecaulfield.bsky.social</a></small></p>


    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai-ethics">ai-ethics</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai-assisted-search">ai-assisted-search</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/hallucinations">hallucinations</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/digital-literacy">digital-literacy</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Sun, 7 Sep 2025 21:45:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Quoting Anil Dash</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/7/anil-dash/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<blockquote cite="https://bsky.app/profile/anildash.com/post/3lybkmj7ast2c"><p>I agree with the intellectual substance of virtually every common critique of AI. And it's very clear that turning those critiques into a competition about who can frame them in the most scathing way online has done <em>zero</em> to slow down adoption, even if much of that is due to default bundling.</p>
<p>At what point are folks going to try literally any other tactic than condescending rants? Does it matter that LLM apps are at the top of virtually every app store nearly every day because individual people are choosing to download them, and the criticism hasn't been effective in slowing that?</p></blockquote>
<p class="cite">&mdash; <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/anildash.com/post/3lybkmj7ast2c">Anil Dash</a></p>

    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai-ethics">ai-ethics</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/anil-dash">anil-dash</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Sun, 7 Sep 2025 21:32:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The SIFT method</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/7/the-sift-method/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://guides.lib.uchicago.edu/c.php?g=1241077&amp;p=9082322">The SIFT method</a></strong></p>
The SIFT method is "an evaluation strategy developed by digital literacy expert, Mike Caulfield, to help determine whether online content can be trusted for credible or reliable sources of information."</p>
<p>This looks <em>extremely</em> useful as a framework for helping people more effectively consume information online (increasingly gathered with <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai-assisted-search/">the help of LLMs</a>).</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Stop</strong>. "Be aware of your emotional response to the headline or information in the article" to protect against clickbait, and don't read further or share until you've applied the other three steps.</li>
<li><strong>Investigate the Source</strong>. Apply <a href="https://pressbooks.pub/webliteracy/chapter/what-reading-laterally-means/">lateral reading</a>, checking what others say about the source rather than just trusting their "about" page.</li>
<li><strong>Find Better Coverage</strong>. "Use lateral reading to see if you can find other sources corroborating the same information or disputing it" and consult trusted fact checkers if necessary.</li>
<li><strong>Trace Claims, Quotes, and Media to their Original Context</strong>. Try to find the original report or referenced material to learn more and check it isn't being represented out of context.</li>
</ul>
<p>This framework really resonates with me: it formally captures and improves on a bunch of informal techniques I've tried to apply in my own work.

    <p><small></small>Via <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/anildash.com/post/3lyavuu6ku22r">@anildash.com</a></small></p>


    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/blogging">blogging</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/research">research</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai-assisted-search">ai-assisted-search</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/digital-literacy">digital-literacy</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Sun, 7 Sep 2025 20:51:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AI mode is good, actually</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/7/ai-mode/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p>When I wrote about <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/research-goblin/">how good ChatGPT with GPT-5</a> is at search yesterday I nearly added a note about how comparatively disappointing Google's efforts around this are.</p>
<p>I'm glad I left that out, because it turns out Google's new "AI mode" is genuinely really good! It feels  very similar to GPT-5 search but returns results <em>much</em> faster.</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://www.google.com/ai">www.google.com/ai</a></strong> (not available in the EU, as I found out this morning since I'm staying in France for a few days.)</p>
<p>Here's <a href="https://share.google/aimode/SZNHD7Owi0Wv9d3Ci">what I got</a> for the following question:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Anthropic but lots of physical books and cut them up and scan them for training data. Do any other AI labs do the same thing?</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img alt="Screenshot of search results page with navigation tabs &quot;AI Mode&quot; and more.  Main search query reads &quot;Anthropic but lots of physical books and cut them up and scan them for training data. Do any other AI labs do the same thing?&quot; Results show &quot;11 sites&quot; and include text: &quot;In 2024, Anthropic paid millions of dollars to buy physical books in bulk, which they then cut up, scanned, and discarded to train their AI models. This method was a major component of a copyright lawsuit settlement that Anthropic paid in September 2025. While Anthropic took this destructive, large-scale approach, other major AI labs have taken different routes to acquire book data.&quot; Followed by &quot;Here's how other AI companies have sourced book data:&quot; with bullet points for &quot;OpenAI and Microsoft: In June 2025, the companies announced a partnership with Harvard University libraries to train AI models on digitized, public-domain books. This non-destructive method provides high-quality text while preserving the original physical copies.&quot; &quot;Meta: Meta has been accused of relying on large-scale piracy to build its datasets for models like LLaMA. In 2025, a search tool revealed that Meta had copied more than 7.5 million books from the pirate site LibGen for its AI systems.&quot; &quot;Google: Decades before the current AI boom, Google pioneered non-destructive scanning methods for its Google Books project. This method became a successful legal precedent for digitizing copyrighted works for internal purposes. In 2024, Anthropic hired the former head of this project, Tom Turvey, to help with its own book-acquisition strategy." src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2025/ai-mode-books.jpg" /></p>
<p>I'll be honest: I hadn't spent much time with AI mode for a couple of reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>My expectations of "AI mode" were extremely low based on my terrible experience of "AI overviews"</li>
<li>The name "AI mode" is so generic!</li>
</ul>
<p>Based on some initial experiments I'm impressed - Google finally seem to be taking full advantage of their search infrastructure for building out truly great AI-assisted search.</p>
<p>I do have one disappointment: AI mode will tell you that it's "running 5 searches" but it won't tell you what those searches are! Seeing the searches that were run is really important for me in evaluating the likely quality of the end results. I've had the same problem with Google's Gemini app in the past - the lack of transparency as to what it's doing really damages my trust.</p>

    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/gemini">gemini</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/google">google</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/search">search</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai-assisted-search">ai-assisted-search</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Sun, 7 Sep 2025 10:08:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>GPT-5 Thinking in ChatGPT (aka Research Goblin) is shockingly good at search</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/research-goblin/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p>"Don't use chatbots as search engines" was great advice for several years... until it wasn't.</p>
<p>I wrote about how good OpenAI's o3 was at using its Bing-backed search tool <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Apr/21/ai-assisted-search/">back in April</a>. GPT-5 feels even better.</p>
<p>I've started calling it my <strong>Research Goblin</strong>. I can assign a task to it, no matter how trivial or complex, and it will do an often unreasonable amount of work to search the internet and figure out an answer.</p>
<p>This is excellent for satisfying curiosity, and occasionally useful for more important endeavors as well.</p>
<p>I always run my searches by selecting the "GPT-5 Thinking" model from the model picker - in my experience this leads to far more comprehensive (albeit much slower) results.</p>
<p>Here are some examples from just the last couple of days. Every single one of them was run on my phone, usually while I was doing something else. Most of them were dictated using the iPhone voice keyboard, which I find faster than typing. Plus, it's fun to talk to my Research Goblin.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/research-goblin/#bouncy-travelators">Bouncy travelators</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/research-goblin/#identify-this-building">Identify this building</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/research-goblin/#starbucks-uk-cake-pops">Starbucks UK cake pops</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/research-goblin/#britannica-to-seed-wikipedia">Britannica to seed Wikipedia</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/research-goblin/#official-name-for-the-university-of-cambridge">Official name for the University of Cambridge</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/research-goblin/#history-of-the-caverns-in-exeter-quay">History of the caverns in Exeter quay</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/research-goblin/#aldi-vs-lidl">Aldi vs Lidl</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/research-goblin/#ai-labs-scanning-books-for-training-data">AI labs scanning books for training data</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/research-goblin/#gpt-5-for-search-feels-competent">GPT-5 for search feels competent</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/research-goblin/#tips-for-using-search-in-chatgpt">Tips for using search in ChatGPT</a></li>
</ul>

<h4 id="bouncy-travelators">Bouncy travelators</h4>
<blockquote>
<p>They used to be rubber bouncy travelators at Heathrow and they were really fun, have all been replaced by metal ones now and if so, when did that happen?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I was traveling through Heathrow airport pondering what had happened to the fun bouncy rubber travelators.</p>
<p><a href="https://chatgpt.com/share/68bc2d98-9aac-8006-98b9-1424d98290f8">Here's what I got</a>. Research Goblin narrowed it down to some time between 2014-2018 but, more importantly, found me this <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/totalsf/article/sfo-bouncy-moving-walkway-airport-19845449.php">delightful 2024 article</a> by Peter Hartlaub in the San Francisco Chronicle with a history of the SFO bouncy walkways, now also sadly retired.</p>
<h4 id="identify-this-building">Identify this building</h4>
<blockquote>
<p><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2025/reading-building.jpg" alt="not a great photo of a building with a distinctive shaped roof" style="max-width: 100%;" /></p>
<p>Identify this building in reading</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is a photo I snapped out of the window on the train. It <a href="https://chatgpt.com/share/68bc2e21-1d24-8006-b083-00b3233e1c67">thought for 1m4s</a> and correctly identified it as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Blade,_Reading">The Blade</a>.</p>
<h2 id="starbucks-uk-cake-pops">Starbucks UK cake pops</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Starbucks in the UK don't sell cake pops! Do a deep investigative dive</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The Starbucks in Exeter railway station didn't have cake pops, and the lady I asked didn't know what they were.</p>
<p><a href="https://chatgpt.com/share/68bc71b4-68f4-8006-b462-cf32f61e7ec3">Here's the result</a>. It turns out Starbucks did launch cake pops in the UK <a href="https://www.nationalworld.com/lifestyle/starbucks-cake-pops-launched-in-uk-on-new-autumn-menu-full-list-of-items-4284537">in September 2023</a> but they aren't available at all outlets, in particular the licensed travel locations such as the one at Exeter St Davids station.</p>
<p>I particularly enjoyed how it established definitive proof by consulting <a href="https://www.starbucks.co.uk/sites/starbucks-uk-pwa/files/2024-11/HOL24_UK_AllergenBook_CORE_FOOD_v02.LR_.pdf">the nutrition and allergen guide PDF</a> on starbucks.co.uk, which does indeed list both the Birthday Cake Pop (my favourite) and the Cookies and Cream one (apparently discontinued in the USA, at least <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/starbucks/comments/1lp5chq/just_learned_today_the_cookies_cream_cake_pop_has/">according to r/starbucks</a>).</p>
<h4 id="britannica-to-seed-wikipedia">Britannica to seed Wikipedia</h4>
<blockquote>
<p>Someone on hacker News said:</p>
<p>&gt; I was looking at another thread about how Wikipedia was the best thing on the internet. But they only got the head start by taking copy of Encyclopedia Britannica and everything else</p>
<p>Find what they meant by that</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://chatgpt.com/share/68bc3062-5a68-8006-a12b-cf7196a130ae">The result</a>. It turns out Wikipedia did seed itself with content from the out-of-copyright 1911 Encyclopædia Britannica... but that project took place in 2006, five years after Wikipedia first launched in 2001.</p>
<p>I asked:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What is the single best article I can link somebody to that explains the 1911 Britannica thing</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And it pointed me to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:WikiProject_Encyclopaedia_Britannica">Wikipedia:WikiProject Encyclopaedia Britannica</a> which includes a detailed explanation and a link to <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:EB1911">the 13,000 pages</a> still tagged with the template from that project. I posted what I found <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45135061#45137109">in a comment</a>.</p>
<p>Notably (for me anyway) I didn't feel the need to disclose my use of ChatGPT in finding that information - at this point that feels a little like disclosing that I ran a Google search.</p>
<h4 id="official-name-for-the-university-of-cambridge">Official name for the University of Cambridge</h4>
<blockquote>
<p>What is the official legal name of the university of Cambridge?</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/iancal/">Here's the context for that one</a>. It thought for 19 seconds - the thinking trace reveals it knew the answer but wanted to confirm it. <a href="https://chatgpt.com/share/68bc723d-a344-8006-9514-fb3ea2c2b43b">It answered</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The Chancellor, Masters, and Scholars of the University of Cambridge.” <a href="https://www.cam.ac.uk/about-the-university/how-the-university-and-colleges-work/the-university-as-a-charity">University of Cambridge</a>, <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/legal">Cambridge University Press &amp; Assessment</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>That first link gave me the citation I needed in order to be sure this was right.</p>
<p>Since this is my shortest example, here's a screenshot of the expanded "Thought for 19s" panel. I <em>always</em> expand the thoughts - seeing how it pulled together its answer is crucial for evaluating if the answer is likely to be useful or not.</p>
<p><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2025/cambridge-name.jpg" alt="Screenshot of an AI assistant's thought process and research. Header shows &quot;Thought for 19s&quot; followed by bullet points: &quot;The user asked for the official legal name of the University of Cambridge, and I think they mean the formal corporate name. It's probably 'The Chancellor, Masters, and Scholars of the University of Cambridge,' similar to Oxford's. I'm going to verify by checking the web for precise information.&quot; &quot;The official name of Cambridge might include the serial comma, like 'Masters, and Scholars.' There's a similar structure with Oxford, which uses a comma after 'Masters' too. The University is an exempt charity, so you can cross-check with legal documents like statutes or charity records. I'll double-check.&quot; Shows search results for &quot;official legal name of University of Cambridge&quot; from en.wikipedia.org, www.cam.ac.uk, projects.propublica.org and &quot;10 more&quot; sources. Continues with &quot;The University of Cambridge's official legal name, based on the University website and Cambridge University Press, is 'The Chancellor, Masters, and Scholars of the University of Cambridge,' with the serial comma after 'Masters.' It's clear from these authoritative sources, so I'll provide that straightforward answer, citing the University site.&quot; &quot;The official legal name of the University of Cambridge is 'The Chancellor, Masters, and Scholars of the University of Cambridge,' with the comma after Masters and the Oxford comma before 'and.' I'll answer concisely in one line and cite official sources to confirm. No need for extra UI elements here.&quot; Shows &quot;Done&quot; status. Final answer displays: &quot;The Chancellor, Masters, and Scholars of the University of Cambridge.&quot; attributed to University of Cambridge, Cambridge University Press &amp; Assessment, with &quot;Sources&quot; section at bottom." style="max-width: 100%;" /></p>
<h4 id="history-of-the-caverns-in-exeter-quay">History of the caverns in Exeter quay</h4>
<blockquote>
<p>Research On the waterfront restaurant in Exeter, is it dug into the cliffs somehow? History of the building, who built it, why and how</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We were out to dinner <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/xxvaPQiNWACtbq3H8">here</a> and noticed that the interior of the restaurant appeared to be a space dug into the cliff, which piqued my interest.</p>
<p>This was <a href="https://chatgpt.com/share/68bc32fb-d52c-8006-9259-0b984dc832b2">the ChatGPT session</a> that inspired the Research Goblin nickname. It just kept on digging!</p>
<p>The first reply took 2m40s and confirmed that yes, these quay buildings were carved into the red sandstone cliff <a href="https://www.exploredevon.info/activities/walk/exeter-quay/">in the 1820s-1830s</a>.</p>
<p>ChatGPT with GPT-5 really likes to suggest additional steps it can take. In this case:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If you’d like, I can dig up the exact Historic England entry that covers the “Southern Warehouse” address and overlay it on a map of the vaults.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I often say "yes" purely out of curiosity to see what it will do next, and the offer to "overlay it on a map" was irresistible, like how would it even do that?</p>
<p>It did a <em>ton</em> of extra searches, found latitude and longitude coordinates for the restaurant (from Wikimedia Commons) and the warehouse buildings (from National Heritage List for England via Wikipedia), showed me that data in a table and then used Python to render this image:</p>
<p><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2025/bad-chart.png" alt="Scatter plot titled &quot;On The Waterfront vs. Warehouse Vaults (Exeter Quay)&quot; with scientific notation &quot;+5.071e1&quot; in top left. Y-axis shows &quot;Latitude&quot; ranging from 0.0065 to 0.0090. X-axis shows &quot;Longitude&quot; ranging from -3.5310 to -3.5280. Three orange X markers plotted: &quot;Warehouse Vaults (6-11, The Quay) — HE 1223046&quot; at top center, &quot;On The Waterfront (4-9 Southern Warehouse)&quot; at middle left, and &quot;Warehouse Vaults (1-4, The Quay) — HE 1223045&quot; at bottom right" style="max-width: 100%;" /></p>
<p>Yeah, so that one is a bit of a miss!</p>
<p>But... the underlying research chain, as always, provided fascinating. I noticed that at one point it had searched for "Exeter Quay vaults map PDF", which inspired my next question:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Did you find any PDF diagrams, showing the tunnels into the cliff</p>
</blockquote>
<p>2m20s later it had found <a href="https://planningdocs.exeter.gov.uk/servlets/direct/KgQ8hlUut3Q2r5wVMItggobi9P/2/844706/1/1/AS_PDF_FILE">a planning document</a> and <a href="https://www.turner-locker.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/08/Cellar-1-The-Quay-TO-LET-2018-1.pdf">a letting brochure</a>, both PDFs, but noted that neither of them had the diagram I wanted. Evidently it actually "reads" the PDFs it finds as part of its activities, since it appears to have knowledge of the images contained within them as well as the text.</p>
<p>It concluded with this intriguing note:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>There’s strong evidence that a detailed plan/section <strong>does</strong> exist in the Exeter Archaeology report often cited by planners—<strong>“Archaeological, Historical and Conservation Study of the Exeter Canal Basin” (Exeter Archaeology Report 00.18, 2000)</strong>—but it isn’t online; it’s just cited in planning documents. You’d likely need to request it via the Devon Heritage Centre/Historic Environment Record.</p>
<p>If you want, I can keep hunting specialist archives for a digitized copy or a different report that includes the vault layouts.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Obviously I said "Yes do that" and 2m24s later it chucked out a whole host of extra links, an apology that it still hadn't found a detailed plan diagram and, under the section heading "What I recommend next (actionable + exact ask)":</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If you’re happy, I can draft an email you can paste to the right archivists. [...]</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Subject: Exeter Quayside cliff vaults – request for plan/section drawings
Hello,</p>
<p>I’m researching the cliff-cut vaults behind The Quay (On The Waterfront / Kings Wharf).
Could you supply scans or copies of any <strong>plans/sections/diagrams</strong> of these vaults—especially those in <strong>Exeter Archaeology Report 00.18 (2000)</strong> (Archaeological, Historical and Conservation Study of the Exeter Canal Basin) and any <strong>EMAFU/Exeter Archaeology drawings</strong> for “The Quay” showing the <strong>vault/tunnel layouts cut into the red sandstone cliff</strong>?</p>
<p>For reference: NHLE list entries <strong>1223045 (1–4 Warehouse Vaults), 1223046 (6–11 Warehouse Vaults)</strong>, and <strong>1223114 (14–25 Vaults)</strong>.</p>
<p>Many thanks!</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p>It's a good thing my Research Goblin doesn't have the ability to send email (which we already know is <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/May/31/snitchbench-with-llm/">very risky business</a>) or at this point I wouldn't be surprised if it started autonomously bothering archivists on my behalf!</p>
<h4 id="aldi-vs-lidl">Aldi vs Lidl</h4>
<blockquote>
<p>In UK supermarket terms compare lidl and aldi</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I saw an Aldi and a Lidl next to each other in Exeter and was curious as to how they compare. In this case my Research Goblin went <em>way</em> deeper than I had intended, thinking for 1m25s about market share and price surveys and loyalty schemes and <a href="https://chatgpt.com/share/68bc7913-7ed8-8006-bd3f-63e540470cd7">answering</a> with ten paragraphs of detailed analysis.</p>
<p>I replied:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Yeah, I just wanted the basic vibes like is one fancier than the other?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It thought for 6 seconds, didn't run any additional searches and replied:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Short version: neither is “fancy” — both are no-frills discounters — but <strong>Lidl often feels a touch more polished</strong>, while <strong>Aldi feels a touch more bare-bones</strong>. [...]</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Since I was now enjoying having my Goblin express judgement over British supermarket chains I said:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>How do they rate in fancinews compared to all of the other major UK supermarket chains?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(That was a typo for "fanciness" which it figured out.)</p>
<p>It thought for another 1m1s, ran 7 searches, consulted 27 URLs and gave me back a ranking that looked about right to me.</p>
<p><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2025/fancy-supermarkets.jpg" alt="ChatGPT. Prompt: How do they rate in fancinews compared to all of the other major UK supermarket chains? Thought for 1m 1s › Gotcha-assuming you mean &quot;fanciness.&quot; Here's the UK supermarket vibe-ladder (posh → no-frills): Super-posh: M&amp;S Food and Waitrose - premium feel, strong store appearance/quality scores; Waitrose is literally described as &quot;upmarket.&quot; Which? The Guardian Upper-mainstream: Sainsbury's, Ocado (online, but it sells M&amp;s Food since 2020, so the range skews premium). Which? The Guardian Mainstream: Tesco, Morrisons, Co-op - broad ranges, middle-of-the-road on experience/ appearance. Which? Value-forward: Asda, Iceland — price-led; Iceland's frozen focus, Asda's value reputation (not &quot;fancy,&quot; but popular). Time Out Worldwide Discounters (least fancy by design): Lidl (a touch more polished in-store) and Aldi (most stripped-back, no-frills). Both sit lower on &quot;store appearance/ service&quot; in consumer surveys, even while smashing value rankings. Which? +1 Net: on a &quot;posh&quot; scale, think M&amp;S/Waitrose at the top, Sainsbury's/Tesco middle, Asda/Iceland lower, and Lidl/Aldi the least fancy— by intent, not as a knock on quality or value." style="max-width: 100%;" /></p>
<h4 id="ai-labs-scanning-books-for-training-data">AI labs scanning books for training data</h4>
<blockquote>
<p>Anthropic bought lots of physical books and cut them up and scan them for training data. Do any other AI labs do the same thing?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Relevant to <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/anthropic-settlement/">today's big story</a>. Research Goblin was <a href="https://chatgpt.com/share/68bc771c-c188-8006-a8e5-4b1624f5bdf0">unable to find</a> any news stories or other evidence that any labs other than Anthropic are engaged in large scale book scanning for training data. That's not to say it isn't happening, but it's happening very quietly if that's the case.</p>
<h4 id="gpt-5-for-search-feels-competent">GPT-5 for search feels competent</h4>
<p>The word that best describes how I feel about GPT-5 search is that it feels <strong>competent</strong>.</p>
<p>I've thrown all sorts of things at it over the last few weeks and it rarely disappoints me. It almost always does better than if I were to dedicate the same amount of time to manually searching myself, mainly because it's much faster at running searches and evaluating the results than I am.</p>
<p>I particularly love that it works so well on mobile. I used to reserve my deeper research sessions to a laptop where I could open up dozens of tabs. I'll still do that for higher stakes activities but I'm finding the scope of curiosity satisfaction I can perform on the go with just my phone has increased quite dramatically.</p>
<p>I've mostly stopped using OpenAI's Deep Research feature, because ChatGPT search now gives me the results I'm interested in far more quickly for most queries.</p>
<p>As a developer who builds software on LLMs I see ChatGPT search as the gold standard for what can be achieved using tool calling combined with chain-of-thought. Techniques like RAG are <em>massively</em> more effective if you can reframe them as several levels of tool calling with a carefully selected set of powerful search tools.</p>
<p>The way that search tool integrates with reasoning is key, because it allows GPT-5 to execute a search, reason about the results and then execute follow-up searches - all as part of that initial "thinking" process.</p>
<p>Anthropic call this ability <a href="https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/build-with-claude/extended-thinking#interleaved-thinking">interleaved thinking</a> and it's also <a href="https://platform.openai.com/docs/guides/reasoning#keeping-reasoning-items-in-context">supported by the OpenAI Responses API</a>.</p>
<h4 id="tips-for-using-search-in-chatgpt">Tips for using search in ChatGPT</h4>
<p>As with all things AI, GPT-5 search rewards intuition gathered through experience. Any time a curious thought pops into my head I try to catch it and throw it at my Research Goblin. If it's something I'm certain it won't be able to handle then even better! I can learn from watching it fail.</p>
<p>I've been trying out hints like "go deep" which seem to trigger a more thorough research job. I enjoy throwing those at shallow and unimportant questions like the UK Starbucks cake pops one just to see what happens!</p>
<p>You can throw questions at it which have a single, unambiguous answer - but I think questions which are broader and don't have a "correct" answer can be a lot more fun. The UK supermarket rankings above are a great example of that.</p>
<p>Since I love a questionable analogy for LLMs Research Goblin is... well, it's a goblin. It's very industrious, not quite human and not entirely trustworthy. You have to be able to outwit it if you want to keep it gainfully employed.</p>
    
        <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/bing">bing</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/search">search</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/openai">openai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llm-tool-use">llm-tool-use</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llm-reasoning">llm-reasoning</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai-assisted-search">ai-assisted-search</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/gpt-5">gpt-5</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Sat, 6 Sep 2025 19:31:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Quoting Jason Liu</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/jason-liu/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<blockquote cite="https://twitter.com/jxnlco/status/1964050092312211636"><p>I am once again shocked at how much better image retrieval performance you can get if you embed highly opinionated summaries of an image, a summary that came out of a visual language model, than using CLIP embeddings themselves. If you tell the LLM that the summary is going to be embedded and used to do search downstream. I had one system go from 28% recall at 5 using CLIP to 75% recall at 5 using an LLM summary.</p></blockquote>
<p class="cite">&mdash; <a href="https://twitter.com/jxnlco/status/1964050092312211636">Jason Liu</a></p>

    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/vision-llms">vision-llms</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/embeddings">embeddings</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/jason-liu">jason-liu</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Sat, 6 Sep 2025 17:20:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kimi-K2-Instruct-0905</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/kimi-k2-instruct-0905/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://huggingface.co/moonshotai/Kimi-K2-Instruct-0905">Kimi-K2-Instruct-0905</a></strong></p>
New not-quite-MIT licensed model from Chinese Moonshot AI, a follow-up to the highly regarded Kimi-K2 model they <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Jul/11/kimi-k2/">released in July</a>.</p>
<p>This one is an incremental improvement - I've seen it referred to online as "Kimi K-2.1". It scores a little higher on a bunch of popular coding benchmarks, reflecting Moonshot's claim that it "demonstrates significant improvements in performance on public benchmarks and real-world coding agent tasks".</p>
<p>More importantly the context window size has been increased from 128,000 to 256,000 tokens.</p>
<p>Like its predecessor this is a <em>big</em> model - 1 trillion parameters in a mixture-of-experts configuration with 384 experts, 32B activated parameters and 8 selected experts per token.</p>
<p>I used <a href="https://console.groq.com/playground?model=moonshotai/kimi-k2-instruct-0905">Groq's playground tool</a> to try "Generate an SVG of a pelican riding a bicycle" and got <a href="https://gist.github.com/simonw/80f9fc8f888edc43e1f2a5170c95de3d">this result</a>, at a very healthy 445 tokens/second taking just under 2 seconds total:</p>
<p><img alt="This one is pretty good. Bicycle is mostly the right shape, the pelican is perched quite awkwardly on the saddle, it has quite a good attempt at the chain mechanism." src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2025/kimi-0905.png" />


    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/groq">groq</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/pelican-riding-a-bicycle">pelican-riding-a-bicycle</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llm-release">llm-release</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai-in-china">ai-in-china</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/moonshot">moonshot</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Sat, 6 Sep 2025 16:59:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Quoting IanCal</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/iancal/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<blockquote cite="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45135302#45135852"><p>RDF has the same problems as the SQL schemas with information scattered. What fields mean requires documentation.</p>
<p>There - they have a name on a person. What name? Given? Legal? Chosen? Preferred for this use case?</p>
<p>You only have one ID for Apple eh? Companies are complex to model, do you mean Apple just as someone would talk about it? The legal structure of entities that underpins all major companies, what part of it is referred to?</p>
<p>I spent a long time building identifiers for universities and companies (which was taken for <a href="https://ror.org/">ROR</a> later) and it was a nightmare to say what a university even was. What’s the name of Cambridge? It’s not “Cambridge University” or “The university of Cambridge” legally. But it also is the actual name as people use it. <em>[It's <a href="https://www.cam.ac.uk/about-the-university/how-the-university-and-colleges-work/the-university-as-a-charity">The Chancellor, Masters, and Scholars of the University of Cambridge</a>]</em></p>
<p>The university of Paris went from something like 13 institutes to maybe one to then a bunch more. Are companies locations at their headquarters? Which headquarters?</p>
<p>Someone will suggest modelling to solve this but here lies the biggest problem:</p>
<p>The correct modelling depends on <em>the questions you want to answer</em>.</p></blockquote>
<p class="cite">&mdash; <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45135302#45135852">IanCal</a>, on Hacker News, discussing RDF</p>

    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/metadata">metadata</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/sql">sql</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/hacker-news">hacker-news</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/rdf">rdf</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Sat, 6 Sep 2025 06:41:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why I think the $1.5 billion Anthropic class action settlement may count as a win for Anthropic</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/6/anthropic-settlement/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://www.theverge.com/anthropic/773087/anthropic-to-pay-1-5-billion-to-authors-in-landmark-ai-settlement">Anthropic to pay $1.5 billion to authors in landmark AI settlement</a></strong></p>
I wrote about <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Jun/24/anthropic-training/">the details of this case</a> when it was found that Anthropic's training on book content was fair use, but they needed to have purchased individual copies of the books first... and they had seeded their collection with pirated ebooks from Books3, PiLiMi and LibGen.</p>
<p>The remaining open question from that case was the penalty for pirating those 500,000 books. That question has now been resolved in a settlement:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Anthropic has reached an agreement to pay “at least” a staggering $1.5 billion, plus interest, to authors to settle its class-action lawsuit. The amount breaks down to smaller payouts expected to be approximately $3,000 per book or work.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It's wild to me that a $1.5 billion settlement can feel like a win for Anthropic, but given that it's undisputed that they downloaded pirated books  (as did Meta and likely many other research teams) the maximum allowed penalty was $150,000 per book, so $3,000 per book is actually a significant discount.</p>
<p>As far as I can tell this case sets a precedent for Anthropic's <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Jun/24/anthropic-training/#purchase-and-scan">more recent approach</a> of buying millions of (mostly used) physical books and destructively scanning them for training as covered by "fair use". I'm not sure if other in-flight legal cases will find differently.</p>
<p>To be clear: it appears it is legal, at least in the USA, to buy a used copy of a physical book (used = the author gets nothing), chop the spine off, scan the pages, discard the paper copy and then train on the scanned content. The transformation from paper to scan is "fair use".</p>
<p>If this <em>does</em> hold it's going to be a great time to be a bulk retailer of used books!</p>
<p><strong>Update</strong>: The official website for the class action lawsuit is <a href="https://www.anthropiccopyrightsettlement.com">www.anthropiccopyrightsettlement.com</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In the coming weeks, and if the court preliminarily approves the settlement, the website will provide to find a full and easily searchable listing of all works covered by the settlement.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the meantime the Atlantic have <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2025/03/search-libgen-data-set/682094/">a search engine</a> to see if your work was included in LibGen, one of the pirated book sources involved in this case.</p>
<p>I had a look and it turns out the book I co-authored with 6 other people back in 2007 <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/the-art/9780980285840/">The Art &amp; Science of JavaScript</a> is in there, so maybe I'm due for 1/7th of one of those $3,000 settlements!</p>
<p><strong>Update 2</strong>: Here's an interesting detail from the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2025/09/05/anthropic-book-authors-copyright-settlement/">Washington Post story</a> about the settlement:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Anthropic said in the settlement that the specific digital copies of books covered by the agreement were not used in the training of its commercially released AI models.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Update 3</strong>: I'm not confident that destroying the scanned books is a hard requirement here - I got that impression from <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/25982181-authors-v-anthropic-ruling/#document/p16">this section</a> of the summary judgment in June:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Here, every purchased print copy was copied in order to save storage space and to enable searchability as a digital copy. The print original was destroyed. One replaced the other. And, there is no evidence that the new, digital copy was shown, shared, or sold outside the company. This use was even more clearly transformative than those in <em>Texaco</em>, <em>Google</em>, and <em>Sony Betamax</em> (where the number of copies went up by at least one), and, of course, more transformative than those uses rejected in <em>Napster</em> (where the number went up by “millions” of copies shared for free with others).</p>
</blockquote>


    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/law">law</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/anthropic">anthropic</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/training-data">training-data</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai-ethics">ai-ethics</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Sat, 6 Sep 2025 05:51:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Quoting Kenton Varda</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/5/kenton-varda/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<blockquote cite="https://twitter.com/KentonVarda/status/1963966469148180839"><p>After struggling for years trying to figure out why people think [Cloudflare] Durable Objects are complicated, I'm increasingly convinced that it's just that they <em>sound</em> complicated.</p>
<p>Feels like we can solve 90% of it by renaming <code>DurableObject</code> to <code>StatefulWorker</code>?</p>
<p>It's just a worker that has state. And because it has state, it also has to have a name, so that you can route to the specific worker that has the state you care about. There may be a sqlite database attached, there may be a container attached. Those are just part of the state.</p></blockquote>
<p class="cite">&mdash; <a href="https://twitter.com/KentonVarda/status/1963966469148180839">Kenton Varda</a></p>

    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/kenton-varda">kenton-varda</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/sqlite">sqlite</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/cloudflare">cloudflare</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 5 Sep 2025 16:43:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Introducing EmbeddingGemma</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/4/embedding-gemma/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://developers.googleblog.com/en/introducing-embeddinggemma/">Introducing EmbeddingGemma</a></strong></p>
Brand new open weights (under the slightly janky <a href="https://ai.google.dev/gemma/terms">Gemma license</a>) 308M parameter embedding model from Google:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Based on the Gemma 3 architecture, EmbeddingGemma is trained on 100+ languages and is small enough to run on less than 200MB of RAM with quantization.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It's available via <a href="https://ai.google.dev/gemma/docs/embeddinggemma/fine-tuning-embeddinggemma-with-sentence-transformers">sentence-transformers</a>, <a href="https://huggingface.co/collections/ggml-org/embeddinggemma-300m-68b2a87d78ca52408f7918f3">llama.cpp</a>, <a href="https://huggingface.co/collections/mlx-community/embeddinggemma-68b9a55aac55466fbd514f7c">MLX</a>, <a href="https://ollama.com/library/embeddinggemma">Ollama</a>, <a href="https://lmstudio.ai/models/google/embedding-gemma-300m">LMStudio</a> and more. </p>
<p>As usual for these smaller models there's a <a href="https://huggingface.co/blog/embeddinggemma#transformersjs">Transformers.js</a> demo (<a href="https://twitter.com/xenovacom/status/1963638444233511016">via</a>) that runs directly in the browser (in Chrome variants) - <a href="https://huggingface.co/spaces/webml-community/semantic-galaxy">Semantic Galaxy</a> loads a ~400MB model and then lets you run embeddings against hundreds of text sentences, map them in a 2D space and run similarity searches to zoom to points within that space.</p>
<p><img alt="Screenshot of The Semantic Galaxy web application interface showing a semantic search tool with a left sidebar containing &quot;Your Dataset&quot; with sample text &quot;The sun peeked through the clouds after a drizzly&quot; and a blue &quot;Generate Galaxy&quot; button, below which is text &quot;Galaxy generated with 106 points. Ready to explore!&quot; followed by &quot;Search Results&quot; listing various text snippets with similarity scores to the search term &quot;pelican riding a bicycle&quot; such as &quot;The cyclist pedaled up the steep hill... 0.491&quot;, &quot;It was so hot that even the birds sou... 0.446&quot;, etc. The main area shows a dark starfield visualization with white dots representing semantic clusters and text snippets floating as labels near the clusters." src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2025/semantic-galaxy-transformers.jpg" />


    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/google">google</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/embeddings">embeddings</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/transformers-js">transformers-js</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/gemma">gemma</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 4 Sep 2025 22:27:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Highlighted tools</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/4/highlighted-tools/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Any time I share my <a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/">collection of tools</a> built using vibe coding and AI-assisted development (now at 124, here's <a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/colophon">the definitive list</a>) someone will inevitably complain that they're mostly trivial.</p>
<p>A lot of them are! Here's a list of some that I think are genuinely useful and worth highlighting:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/ocr">OCR PDFs and images directly in your browser</a>. This is the tool that started the collection, and I still use it on a regular basis. You can open any PDF in it (even PDFs that are just scanned images with no embedded text) and it will extract out the text so you can copy-and-paste it. It uses PDF.js and Tesseract.js to do that entirely in the browser. I wrote about <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Mar/30/ocr-pdfs-images/">how I originally built that here</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/annotated-presentations">Annotated Presentation Creator</a> - this one is <em>so useful</em>. I use it to turn talks that I've given into full annotated presentations, where each slide is accompanied by detailed notes. I have <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/annotated-talks/">29 blog entries</a> like that now and most of them were written with the help of this tool. Here's <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2023/Aug/6/annotated-presentations/">how I built that</a>, plus <a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/colophon#annotated-presentations.html">follow-up prompts I used to improve it</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/image-resize-quality">Image resize, crop, and quality comparison</a> - I use this for every single image I post to my blog. It lets me drag (or paste) an image onto the page and then shows me a comparison of different sizes and quality settings, each of which I can download and then upload to my S3 bucket. I recently added a slightly janky but mobile-accessible cropping tool as well. <a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/colophon#image-resize-quality.html">Prompts</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/social-media-cropper">Social Media Card Cropper</a> - this is an even more useful image tool. Bluesky, Twitter etc all benefit from a 2x1 aspect ratio "card" image. I built this custom tool for creating those - you can paste in an image and crop and zoom it to the right dimensions. I use this all the time. <a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/colophon#social-media-cropper.html">Prompts</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/svg-render">SVG to JPEG/PNG</a> - every time I publish an <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/pelican-riding-a-bicycle/">SVG of a pelican riding a bicycle</a> I use this tool to turn that SVG into a JPEG or PNG. <a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/colophon#svg-render.html">Prompts</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/encrypt">Encrypt / decrypt message</a> - I often run workshops where I want to distribute API keys to the workshop participants. This tool lets me encrypt a message with a passphrase, then share the resulting URL to the encrypted message and tell people (with a note on a slide) how to decrypt it. <a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/colophon#encrypt.html">Prompt</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/jina-reader">Jina Reader</a> - enter a URL, get back a Markdown version of the page. It's a thin wrapper over the Jina Reader API, but it's useful because it adds a "copy to clipboard" button which means it's one of the fastest way to turn a webpage into data on a clipboard on my mobile phone. I use this several times a week. <a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/colophon#jina-reader.html">Prompts</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.llm-prices.com/">llm-prices.com</a> - a pricing comparison and token pricing calculator for various hosted LLMs. This one started out as a tool but graduated to its own domain name. Here's the <a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/colophon#llm-prices.html">prompting development history</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/open-sauce-2025">Open Sauce 2025</a> - an unofficial schedule for the Open Sauce conference, complete with option to export to ICS plus a search tool and now-and-next. I built this <em>entirely on my phone</em> using OpenAI Codex, including scraping the official schedule - <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Jul/17/vibe-scraping/">full details here</a>. </li>
<li><a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/hacker-news-histogram">Hacker News Multi-Term Histogram</a> - compare search terms on Hacker News to see how their relative popularity changed over time. <a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/colophon#hacker-news-histogram.html">Prompts</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/passkeys">Passkey experiment</a> - a UI for trying out the Passkey / WebAuthn APIs that are built into browsers these days. <a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/colophon#passkeys.html">Prompts</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/incomplete-json-printer">Incomplete JSON Pretty Printer</a> - do you ever find yourself staring at a screen full of JSON that isn't completely valid because it got truncated? This tool will pretty-print it anyway. <a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/colophon#incomplete-json-printer.html">Prompts</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/bluesky-firehose">Bluesky WebSocket Feed Monitor</a> - I found out Bluesky has a Firehose API that can be accessed directly from the browser, so I vibe-coded up this tool to try it out. <a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/colophon#bluesky-firehose.html">Prompts</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>In putting this list together I realized I wanted to be able to link to the prompts for each tool... but those were hidden inside a collapsed <code>&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;</code> element for each one. So I fired up <a href="https://openai.com/codex/">OpenAI Codex</a> and prompted:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>Update the script that builds the colophon.html page such that the generated page has a tiny bit of extra JavaScript - when the page is loaded as e.g. https://tools.simonwillison.net/colophon#jina-reader.html it should notice the #jina-reader.html fragment identifier and ensure that the Development history details/summary for that particular tool is expanded when the page loads.</code></p>
</blockquote>
<p>It <a href="https://github.com/simonw/tools/pull/47">authored this PR for me</a> which fixed the problem.</p>

    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/vibe-coding">vibe-coding</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai-assisted-programming">ai-assisted-programming</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/tools">tools</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/projects">projects</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/coding-agents">coding-agents</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 4 Sep 2025 21:58:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Beyond Vibe Coding</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/4/beyond-vibe-coding/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://beyond.addy.ie/">Beyond Vibe Coding</a></strong></p>
Back in May I wrote <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/May/1/not-vibe-coding/">Two publishers and three authors fail to understand what “vibe coding” means</a> where I called out the authors of two forthcoming books on "vibe coding" for abusing that term to refer to all forms of AI-assisted development, when <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Mar/19/vibe-coding/">Not all AI-assisted programming is vibe coding</a> based on the <a href="https://twitter.com/karpathy/status/1886192184808149383">original Karpathy definition</a>.</p>
<p>I'll be honest: I don't feel great about that post. I made an example of those two books to push my own agenda of encouraging "vibe coding" to avoid <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Mar/23/semantic-diffusion/">semantic diffusion</a> but it felt (and feels) a bit mean.</p>
<p>... but maybe it had an effect? I recently spotted that Addy Osmani's book "Vibe Coding: The Future of Programming" has a new title, it's now called "Beyond Vibe Coding: From Coder to AI-Era Developer".</p>
<p>This title is <strong>so much better</strong>. Setting aside my earlier opinions, this positioning as a book to help people go <em>beyond</em> vibe coding and use LLMs as part of a professional engineering practice is a really great hook!</p>
<p>From Addy's new description of the book:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Vibe coding was never meant to describe all AI-assisted coding. It's a specific approach where you don't read the AI's code before running it. There's much more to consider beyond the prototype for production systems. [...]</p>
<p>AI-assisted engineering is a more structured approach that combines the creativity of vibe coding with the rigor of traditional engineering practices. It involves specs, rigor and emphasizes collaboration between human developers and AI tools, ensuring that the final product is not only functional but also maintainable and secure.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Amazon <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Beyond-Vibe-Coding-Leveraging-AI-Assisted/dp/B0F6S5425Y">lists it</a> as releasing on September 23rd. I'm looking forward to it.</p>
<p><img alt="O'Reilly book cover: Beyond Vibe Coding: From Coder to AI-Era Developer, by Addy Osmani. Features two hummingbirds, presumably because their wings vibrate!" src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2025/beyond-vibe-coding.jpg" />


    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/books">books</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/oreilly">oreilly</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai-assisted-programming">ai-assisted-programming</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/addy-osmani">addy-osmani</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/vibe-coding">vibe-coding</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 4 Sep 2025 20:58:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Google antitrust remedies</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/3/antitrust/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.dcd.223205/gov.uscourts.dcd.223205.1436.0_1.pdf">gov.uscourts.dcd.223205.1436.0_1.pdf</a></strong></p>
Here's the 230 page PDF ruling on the 2023 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_v._Google_LLC_(2023)">United States v. Google LLC federal antitrust case</a> - the case that could have resulted in Google selling off Chrome and cutting most of Mozilla's funding.</p>
<p>I made it through the first dozen pages - it's actually quite readable.</p>
<p>It opens with a clear summary of the case so far, bold highlights mine:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Last year, this court ruled that Defendant Google LLC had violated Section 2 of the Sherman Act: “Google is a monopolist, and it has acted as one to maintain its monopoly.” <strong>The court found that, for more than a decade, Google had entered into distribution agreements with browser developers, original equipment manufacturers, and wireless carriers to be the out-of-the box, default general search engine (“GSE”) at key search access points</strong>. These access points were the most efficient channels for distributing a GSE, and Google paid billions to lock them up. The agreements harmed competition. <strong>They prevented rivals from accumulating the queries and associated data, or scale, to effectively compete and discouraged investment and entry into the market</strong>. And they enabled Google to earn monopoly profits from its search text ads, to amass an unparalleled volume of scale to improve its search product, and to remain the default GSE without fear of being displaced. Taken together, these agreements effectively “froze” the search ecosystem, resulting in markets in which Google has “no true competitor.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There's an interesting generative AI twist: when the case was first argued in 2023 generative AI wasn't an influential issue, but more recently Google seem to be arguing that it is an existential threat that they need to be able to take on without additional hindrance:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The emergence of GenAl changed the course of this case. No witness at the liability trial testified that GenAl products posed a near-term threat to GSEs. <strong>The very first witness at the remedies hearing, by contrast, placed GenAl front and center as a nascent competitive threat</strong>. These remedies proceedings thus have been as much about promoting competition among GSEs as ensuring that Google’s dominance in search does not carry over into the GenAlI space. Many of Plaintiffs’ proposed remedies are crafted with that latter objective in mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I liked this note about the court's challenges in issuing effective remedies:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Notwithstanding this power, courts must approach the task of crafting remedies with a healthy dose of humility. This court has done so. It has no expertise in the business of GSEs, the buying and selling of search text ads, or the engineering of GenAl technologies. <strong>And, unlike the typical case where the court’s job is to resolve a dispute based on historic facts, here the court is asked to gaze into a crystal ball and look to the future. Not exactly a judge’s forte</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>On to the remedies. These ones looked particularly important to me:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Google will be barred from entering or maintaining any exclusive contract
relating to the distribution of Google Search, Chrome, Google Assistant,
and the Gemini app. [...]</li>
<li>Google will not be required to divest Chrome; nor will the court include a
contingent divestiture of the Android operating system in the final
judgment. Plaintiffs overreached in seeking forced divesture of these key
assets, which Google did not use to effect any illegal restraints. [...]</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>I guess Perplexity <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/c3dpr0kkyz4o">won't be buying Chrome</a> then!</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Google will not be barred from making payments or offering other
consideration to distribution partners for preloading or placement of Google
Search, Chrome, or its GenAl products. <strong>Cutting off payments from Google
almost certainly will impose substantial —in some cases, crippling—
downstream harms to distribution partners</strong>, related markets, and consumers,
which counsels against a broad payment ban.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>That looks like a huge sigh of relief for Mozilla, who were at risk of losing a sizable portion of their income if Google's search distribution revenue were to be cut off.

    <p><small></small>Via <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45108548">Hacker News</a></small></p>


    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/chrome">chrome</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/google">google</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/law">law</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/mozilla">mozilla</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 3 Sep 2025 08:56:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Making XML human-readable without XSLT</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/2/making-xml-human-readable-without-xslt/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://jakearchibald.com/2025/making-xml-human-readable-without-xslt/">Making XML human-readable without XSLT</a></strong></p>
In response to the <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Aug/19/xslt/">recent discourse</a> about XSLT support in browsers, Jake Archibald shares a new-to-me alternative trick for making an XML document readable in a browser: adding the following element near the top of the XML:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;script
  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
  src="script.js" defer="" /&gt;
</code></pre>
<p>That <code>script.js</code> will then be executed by the browser, and can swap out the XML with HTML by creating new elements using the correct namespace:</p>
<pre><code>const htmlEl = document.createElementNS(
  'http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml',
  'html',
);
document.documentElement.replaceWith(htmlEl);
// Now populate the new DOM
</code></pre>


    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/browsers">browsers</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/javascript">javascript</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/rss">rss</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/xml">xml</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/xslt">xslt</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/jake-archibald">jake-archibald</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 2 Sep 2025 19:32:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rich Pixels</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/2/rich-pixels/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://github.com/darrenburns/rich-pixels">Rich Pixels</a></strong></p>
Neat Python library by Darren Burns adding pixel image support to the Rich terminal library, using tricks to render an image using full or half-height colored blocks.</p>
<p>Here's <a href="https://github.com/darrenburns/rich-pixels/blob/a0745ebcc26b966d9dbac5875720364ee5c6a1d3/rich_pixels/_renderer.py#L123C25-L123C26">the key trick</a> - it renders Unicode ▄ (U+2584, "lower half block") characters after setting a foreground and background color for the two pixels it needs to display.</p>
<p>I got GPT-5 to <a href="https://chatgpt.com/share/68b6c443-2408-8006-8f4a-6862755cd1e4">vibe code up</a> a <code>show_image.py</code> terminal command which resizes the provided image to fit the width and height of the current terminal and displays it using Rich Pixels. That <a href="https://github.com/simonw/tools/blob/main/python/show_image.py">script is here</a>, you can run it with <code>uv</code> like this:</p>
<pre><code>uv run https://tools.simonwillison.net/python/show_image.py \
  image.jpg
</code></pre>
<p>Here's what I got when I ran it against my V&amp;A East Storehouse photo from <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Aug/27/london-culture/">this post</a>:</p>
<p><img alt="Terminal window. I ran that command and it spat out quite a pleasing and recognizable pixel art version of the photograph." src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2025/pixel-storehouse.jpg" />


    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ascii-art">ascii-art</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/cli">cli</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/python">python</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/uv">uv</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/vibe-coding">vibe-coding</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/gpt-5">gpt-5</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/rich">rich</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 2 Sep 2025 11:05:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>August 2025 newsletter</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/1/august-2025/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p>I just sent out my August 2025 <strong><a href="https://github.com/sponsors/simonw">sponsors-only newsletter</a></strong> summarizing the past month in LLMs and my other work. Topics included GPT-5, gpt-oss, image editing models (Qwen-Image-Edit and Gemini Nano Banana), other significant model releases and the tools I'm using at the moment.</p>
<p>If you'd like a preview of the newsletter, here's <a href="https://gist.github.com/simonw/722fc2f242977cb185838353776d14f4">the July 2025 edition</a> I sent out a month ago.</p>
<p>New sponsors get access to the full archive. If you start sponsoring for $10/month or more right now you'll get instant access to <a href="https://github.com/simonw-private/monthly/blob/main/2025-08-august.md">the August edition</a> in my <code>simonw-private/monthly</code> GitHub repository.</p>
<p>If you've already read <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Aug/">all 85 posts</a> I wrote in August the newsletter acts mainly as a recap, but I've had positive feedback from people who prefer to get the monthly edited highlights over reading the firehose that is my blog!</p>
<p>Here's the table of contents for the August newsletter:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>GPT-5</li>
<li>OpenAl's open models: gpt-oss-120b and gpt-oss-20b</li>
<li>Other significant model releases in
August</li>
<li>Image editing: Qwen-Image-Edit and
Gemini Nano Banana</li>
<li>More prompt injection and more lethal trifecta</li>
<li>Tools I'm using at the moment</li>
<li>Bonus links</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/newsletter">newsletter</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 1 Sep 2025 19:41:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Introducing gpt-realtime</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/1/introducing-gpt-realtime/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-gpt-realtime/">Introducing gpt-realtime</a></strong></p>
Released a few days ago (August 28th), <code>gpt-realtime</code> is OpenAI's new "most advanced speech-to-speech model". It looks like this is a replacement for the older <code>gpt-4o-realtime-preview</code> model that was released <a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-the-realtime-api/">last October</a>.</p>
<p>This is a slightly confusing release. The previous realtime model was clearly described as a variant of GPT-4o, sharing the same October 2023 training cut-off date as that model.</p>
<p>I had expected that <code>gpt-realtime</code> might be a GPT-5 relative, but its training date is still October 2023 whereas GPT-5 is September 2024.</p>
<p><code>gpt-realtime</code> also shares the relatively low 32,000 context token and 4,096 maximum output token limits of <code>gpt-4o-realtime-preview</code>.</p>
<p>The only reference I found to GPT-5 in the documentation for the new model was a note saying "Ambiguity and conflicting instructions degrade performance, similar to GPT-5."</p>
<p>The <a href="https://platform.openai.com/docs/guides/realtime-models-prompting#general-usage-tips">usage tips</a> for <code>gpt-realtime</code> have a few surprises:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Iterate relentlessly</strong>. Small wording changes can make or break behavior.</p>
<p>Example: Swapping “inaudible” → “unintelligible” improved noisy input handling. [...]</p>
<p><strong>Convert non-text rules to text</strong>: The model responds better to clearly written text.</p>
<p>Example: Instead of writing, "IF x &gt; 3 THEN ESCALATE", write, "IF MORE THAN THREE FAILURES THEN ESCALATE."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There are a whole lot more prompting tips in the new <a href="https://cookbook.openai.com/examples/realtime_prompting_guide">Realtime Prompting Guide</a>.</p>
<p>OpenAI list several key improvements to <code>gpt-realtime</code> including the ability to configure it with a list of MCP servers, "better instruction following" and the ability to send it images.</p>
<p>My biggest confusion came from <a href="https://openai.com/api/pricing/">the pricing page</a>, which lists separate pricing for using the Realtime API with <code>gpt-realtime</code> and GPT-4o mini. This suggests to me that the old <a href="https://platform.openai.com/docs/models/gpt-4o-mini-realtime-preview">gpt-4o-mini-realtime-preview</a> model is still available, despite it no longer being listed on the <a href="https://platform.openai.com/docs/models">OpenAI models page</a>.</p>
<p><code>gpt-4o-mini-realtime-preview</code> is a <strong>lot</strong> cheaper:</p>
<table>
    <thead>
        <tr>
            <th>Model</th>
            <th>Token Type</th>
            <th>Input</th>
            <th>Cached Input</th>
            <th>Output</th>
        </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td rowspan="3">gpt-realtime</td>
            <td>Text</td>
            <td>$4.00</td>
            <td>$0.40</td>
            <td>$16.00</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>Audio</td>
            <td>$32.00</td>
            <td>$0.40</td>
            <td>$64.00</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>Image</td>
            <td>$5.00</td>
            <td>$0.50</td>
            <td>-</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td rowspan="2">gpt-4o-mini-realtime-preview</td>
            <td>Text</td>
            <td>$0.60</td>
            <td>$0.30</td>
            <td>$2.40</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>Audio</td>
            <td>$10.00</td>
            <td>$0.30</td>
            <td>$20.00</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>

<p>The mini model also has a much longer 128,000 token context window.</p>
<p><strong>Update</strong>: Turns out that was <a href="https://twitter.com/_agamble/status/1962839472837361807">a mistake in the documentation</a>, that mini model has a 16,000 token context size.</p>
<p><strong>Update 2</strong>: OpenAI's <a href="https://twitter.com/pbbakkum/status/1962901822135525695">Peter Bakkum clarifies</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>There are different voice models in API and ChatGPT, but they share some recent improvements. The voices are also different.</p>
<p>gpt-realtime has a mix of data specific enough to itself that its not really 4o or 5</p>
</blockquote>


    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/audio">audio</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/realtime">realtime</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/openai">openai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llm-pricing">llm-pricing</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/multi-modal-output">multi-modal-output</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llm-release">llm-release</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 1 Sep 2025 17:34:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cloudflare Radar: AI Insights</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/1/cloudflare-radar-ai-insights/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://radar.cloudflare.com/ai-insights">Cloudflare Radar: AI Insights</a></strong></p>
Cloudflare launched this dashboard <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/expanded-ai-insights-on-cloudflare-radar/">back in February</a>, incorporating traffic analysis from Cloudflare's network along with insights from their popular 1.1.1.1 DNS service.</p>
<p>I found this chart particularly interesting, showing which documented AI crawlers are most active collecting training data - lead by GPTBot, ClaudeBot and Meta-ExternalAgent:</p>
<p><img alt="Line chart showing HTTP traffic by bot over time from August 26 to September 1. HTTP traffic by bot - HTTP request trends for top five most active AI bots. Crawl purpose: Training. GPTBot 31.7% (orange line), ClaudeBot 27.1% (blue line), Meta-ExternalAgent 25.3% (light blue line), Bytespider 9.3% (yellow-green line), Applebot 5.2% (green line). Max scale shown on y-axis. X-axis shows dates: Tue, Aug 26, Wed, Aug 27, Thu, Aug 28, Fri, Aug 29, Sat, Aug 30, Sun, Aug 31, Mon, Sep 1. Top right shows Crawl purpose dropdown set to &quot;Training&quot; with X and checkmark buttons." src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2025/http-traffic-by-bot.jpg" /></p>
<p>Cloudflare's DNS data also hints at the popularity of different services. ChatGPT holds the first place, which is unsurprising - but second place is a hotly contested race between Claude and Perplexity and #4/#5/#6 is contested by GitHub Copilot, Perplexity, and Codeium/Windsurf.</p>
<p>Google Gemini comes in 7th, though since this is DNS based I imagine this is undercounting instances of Gemini on <code>google.com</code> as opposed to <code>gemini.google.com</code>.</p>
<p><img alt="Line chart showing generative AI services popularity rankings over time. Title: &quot;Generative AI services popularity&quot; with subtitle &quot;Top 10 services based on 1.1.1.1 DNS resolver traffic&quot; and question mark and share icons. Legend shows: ChatGPT/OpenAI (dark blue), Character.AI (light blue), Claude/Anthropic (orange), Perplexity (olive green), GitHub Copilot (green), Codeium/Windsurf AI (pink), Google Gemini (purple), QuillBot (red), Grok/xAI (brown), DeepSeek (yellow). Y-axis shows ranks #1-#10, X-axis shows dates from Mon, Aug 25 to Mon, Sep 1 (partially visible). ChatGPT maintains #1 position throughout. Other services show various ranking changes over the week-long period." src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2025/cloudflare-gen-ai.jpg" />

    <p><small></small>Via <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45093090">Hacker News</a></small></p>


    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/crawling">crawling</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/dns">dns</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/cloudflare">cloudflare</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 1 Sep 2025 17:06:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Claude Opus 4.1 and Opus 4 degraded quality</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Aug/30/claude-degraded-quality/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://status.anthropic.com/incidents/h26lykctfnsz">Claude Opus 4.1 and Opus 4 degraded quality</a></strong></p>
Notable because often when people complain of degraded model quality it turns out to be unfounded - Anthropic in the past have emphasized that they don't change the model weights after releasing them without changing the version number.</p>
<p>In this case a botched upgrade of their inference stack cause a genuine model degradation for 56.5 hours:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>From 17:30 UTC on Aug 25th to 02:00 UTC on Aug 28th, Claude Opus 4.1 experienced a degradation in quality for some requests. Users may have seen lower intelligence, malformed responses or issues with tool calling in Claude Code.</p>
<p>This was caused by a rollout of our inference stack, which we have since rolled back for Claude Opus 4.1. [...]</p>
<p>We’ve also discovered that Claude Opus 4.0 has been affected by the same issue and we are in the process of rolling it back.</p>
</blockquote>


    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/anthropic">anthropic</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/claude">claude</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/claude-4">claude-4</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2025 21:04:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Quoting Benj Edwards</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Aug/30/benj-edwards/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<blockquote cite="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2025/08/the-personhood-trap-how-ai-fakes-human-personality/"><p>LLMs are intelligence without agency—what we might call "vox sine persona": voice without person. Not the voice of someone, not even the collective voice of many someones, but a voice emanating from no one at all.</p></blockquote>
<p class="cite">&mdash; <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2025/08/the-personhood-trap-how-ai-fakes-human-personality/">Benj Edwards</a></p>

    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/benj-edwards">benj-edwards</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai-personality">ai-personality</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2025 06:52:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Talk Python: Celebrating Django&apos;s 20th Birthday With Its Creators</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Aug/29/talk-python/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://talkpython.fm/episodes/show/518/celebrating-djangos-20th-birthday-with-its-creators">Talk Python: Celebrating Django&#x27;s 20th Birthday With Its Creators</a></strong></p>
I recorded this podcast episode recently to celebrate Django's 20th birthday with Adrian Holovaty, Will Vincent, Jeff Triplet, and Thibaud Colas.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We didn’t know that it was a web framework. We thought it was a tool for building local newspaper websites. [...]</p>
<p>Django’s original tagline was ‘Web development on journalism deadlines’. That’s always been my favorite description of the project.</p>
</blockquote>


    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/adrian-holovaty">adrian-holovaty</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/django">django</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/python">python</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/podcast-appearances">podcast-appearances</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 20:02:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The perils of vibe coding</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Aug/29/the-perils-of-vibe-coding/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://www.ft.com/content/5b3d410a-6e02-41ad-9e0a-c2e4d672ca00">The perils of vibe coding</a></strong></p>
I was interviewed by Elaine Moore for this opinion piece in the Financial Times, which ended up in the print edition of the paper too! I picked up a copy yesterday:</p>
<p><a href="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2025/ft.jpeg" style="text-decoration: none; border-bottom: none"><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2025/ft.jpeg" alt="The perils of vibe coding - A new OpenAI model arrived this month with a glossy livestream, group watch parties and a lingering sense of disappointment. The YouTube comment section was underwhelmed. “I think they are all starting to realize this isn’t going to become the world like they thought it would,” wrote one viewer. “I can see it on their faces.” But if the casual user was unimpressed, the AI model’s saving grace may be vibe. Coding is generative AI’s newest battleground. With big bills to pay, high valuations to live up to and a market wobble to erase, the sector needs to prove its corporate productivity chops. Coding is hardly promoted as a business use case that already works. For one thing, AI-generated code holds the promise of replacing programmers — a profession of very well paid people. For another, the work can be quantified. In April, Microsoft chief executive Satya Nadella said that up to 50 per cent of the company’s code was now being written by AI. Google chief executive Sundar Pichai has said the same thing. Salesforce has paused engineering hires and Mark Zuckerberg told podcaster Joe Rogan that Meta would use AI as a “mid-level engineer” that writes code. Meanwhile, start-ups such as Replit and Cursor’s Anysphere are trying to persuade people that with AI, anyone can code. In theory, every employee can become a software engineer. So why aren’t we? One possibility is that it’s all still too unfamiliar. But when I ask people who write code for a living they offer an alternative suggestion: unpredictability. As programmer Simon Willison put it: “A lot of people are missing how weird and funny this space is. I’ve been a computer programmer for 30 years and [AI models] don’t behave like normal computers.” Willison is well known in the software engineering community for his AI experiments. He’s an enthusiastic vibe coder — using LLMs to generate code using natural language prompts. OpenAI’s latest model GPT-3.1s, he is now favourite. Still, he predicts that a vibe coding crash is due if it is used to produce glitchy software. It makes sense that programmers — people who are interested in finding new ways to solve problems — would be early adopters of LLMs. Code is a language, albeit an abstract one. And generative AI is trained in nearly all of them, including older ones like Cobol. That doesn’t mean they accept all of its suggestions. Willison thinks the best way to see what a new model can do is to ask for something unusual. He likes to request an svg (an image made out of lines described with code) of a pelican on a bike and asks it to remember the chickens in his garden by name. Results can be bizarre. One model ignored key prompts in favour of composing a poem. Still, his adventures in vibe coding sound like an advert for the sector’s future. Anthropic’s Claude Code, the favoured model for developers, to make an OCR (optical character recognition) software loves screenshots) tool that will copy and paste text from a screenshot. He wrote software that summarises blog comments and has planned to cut a custom tool that will alert him when a whale is visible from his Pacific coast home. All this by typing prompts in English. It’s sounds like the sort of thing Bill Gates might have had in mind when he wrote that natural language AI agents would bring about “the biggest revolution in computing since we went from typing commands to tapping on icons”. But watching code appear and know how it works are two different things. My efforts to make my own comment summary tool produced something unworkable that gave overly long answers and then congratulated itself as a success. Willison says he wouldn’t use AI-generated code for projects he planned to ship out unless he had reviewed each line. Not only is there the risk of hallucination but the chatbot’s desire to be agreeable means it may an unusable idea works. That is a particular issue for those of us who don’t know how to fix the code. We risk creating software with hidden problems. It may not save time either. A study published in July by the non-profit Model Evaluation and Threat Research assessed work done by 16 developers — some with AI tools, some without. Those using AI assistance it had made them faster. In fact it took them nearly a fifth longer. Several developers I spoke to said AI was best used as a way to talk through coding problems. It’s a version of something they call rubber ducking (after their habit of talking to the toys on their desk) — only this rubber duck can talk back. As one put it, code shouldn’t be judged by volume or speed. Progress in AI coding is tangible. But measuring productivity gains is not as neat as a simple percentage calculation."></a></p>
<p>From the article, with links added by me to relevant projects:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Willison thinks the best way to see what a new model can do is to ask for something unusual. He likes to request an SVG (an image made out of lines described with code) of <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/pelican-riding-a-bicycle/">a pelican on a bike</a> and asks it to remember the chickens in his garden by name. Results can be bizarre. One model ignored his prompts in favour of <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Aug/14/gemma-3-270m/">composing a poem</a>.</p>
<p>Still, his adventures in vibe coding sound like an advert for the sector. He used Anthropic's Claude Code, the favoured model for developers, to <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2024/Mar/30/ocr-pdfs-images/">make an OCR</a> (optical character recognition - software loves acronyms) tool that will copy and paste text from a screenshot.</p>
<p>He wrote software that <a href="https://til.simonwillison.net/llms/claude-hacker-news-themes">summarises blog comments</a> and has plans to build a custom tool that will alert him when a whale is visible from his Pacific coast home. All this by typing prompts in English.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I've been talking about that whale spotting project for far too long. Now that it's been in the FT I really need to build it.</p>
<p>(On the subject of OCR... I tried extracting the text from the above image using GPT-5 and got a <a href="https://chatgpt.com/share/68b1e707-add0-8006-8344-4c2fca902b2e">surprisingly bad result</a> full of hallucinated details. Claude Opus 4.1 <a href="https://claude.ai/share/e98d2fe1-0c81-4f51-8739-483f843e4c0e">did a lot better</a> but still made some mistakes. Gemini 2.5 <a href="https://aistudio.google.com/app/prompts?state=%257B%2522ids%2522:%255B%25221MOzgBJI-FJF1uyile_7h2zL4F6lD0sgK%2522%255D,%2522action%2522:%2522open%2522,%2522userId%2522:%2522106366615678321494423%2522,%2522resourceKeys%2522:%257B%257D%257D&amp;usp=sharing,%20https://drive.google.com/file/d/1ffD88ORjgjFzbPsvQ-Z52Exhb_Z9MgtL/view?usp=sharing">did much better</a>.)


    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ocr">ocr</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/claude">claude</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/vibe-coding">vibe-coding</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/press-quotes">press-quotes</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/gpt-5">gpt-5</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 17:51:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lossy encyclopedia</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Aug/29/lossy-encyclopedia/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Since I love collecting questionable analogies for LLMs, here's a new one I just came up with: an LLM is <strong>a lossy encyclopedia</strong>. They have a huge array of facts compressed into them but that compression is lossy (see also <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/tech/annals-of-technology/chatgpt-is-a-blurry-jpeg-of-the-web">Ted Chiang</a>).</p>
<p>The key thing is to develop an intuition for questions it can usefully answer vs questions that are at a level of detail where the lossiness matters.</p>
<p>This thought sparked by <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45058688#45060519">a comment</a> on Hacker News asking why an LLM couldn't "Create a boilerplate Zephyr project skeleton, for Pi Pico with st7789 spi display drivers configured". That's more of a lossless encyclopedia question!</p>
<p>My <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45058688#45060709">answer</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The way to solve this particular problem is to make a correct example available to it. Don't expect it to just know extremely specific facts like that - instead, treat it as a tool that can act on facts presented to it.</p>
</blockquote>

    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 09:26:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Python: The Documentary</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Aug/28/python-the-documentary/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://youtu.be/GfH4QL4VqJ0">Python: The Documentary</a></strong></p>
New documentary about the origins of the Python programming language - 84 minutes long, built around extensive interviews with Guido van Rossum and others who were there at the start and during the subsequent journey.


    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/computer-history">computer-history</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/guido-van-rossum">guido-van-rossum</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/python">python</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/youtube">youtube</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 19:49:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>V&amp;A East Storehouse and Operation Mincemeat in London</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Aug/27/london-culture/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p>We were back in London for a few days and yesterday had a day of culture.</p>
<p>First up: the brand new <a href="https://www.vam.ac.uk/east/storehouse/visit">V&amp;A East Storehouse</a> museum in the Queen Elizabeth Olympic Park near Stratford, which opened on May 31st this year.</p>
<p>This is a delightful new format for a museum. The building is primarily an off-site storage area for London's Victoria and Albert museum, storing 250,000 items that aren't on display in their main building.</p>
<p>The twist is that it's also open to the public. Entrance is free, and you can climb stairs and walk through an airlock-style corridor into the climate controlled interior, then explore three floors of walkways between industrial shelving units holding thousands of items from the collection.</p>
<p>There is almost no signage aside from an occasional number that can help you look up items in the online catalog.</p>
<p>I found the lack of signs to be unexpectedly delightful: it compels you to really pay attention to the items on display.</p>
<p>There's so much great stuff in here. I particularly appreciated the two storey street-facing façades of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robin_Hood_Gardens">Robin Hood Gardens</a>, a brutalist London residential estate completed in 1972 and demolished in 2017 through 2025. I also really enjoyed the Kaufman Office, an office space transplanted from Pittsburgh that is "the only complete interior designed by architect Frank Lloyd Wright on permanent display outside the USA."</p>
<p><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2025/v-a-east-1.jpg" alt="Three levels of the Storehouse, each with walkways full of people looking at a variety of exhibits on shelves. Two huge concrete facades from the Robin Hood Gardens hang between the floors." style="max-width: 100%;" /></p>
<p>The building is a working museum warehouse and preservation facility, and there are various points where you can look out into the rest of the space (I enjoyed spotting a cluster of grandfather clocks in the distance) or watch the curators arranging and preserving new artifacts.</p>
<p>I've <a href="https://www.niche-museums.com/113">added it to Niche Museums</a> with whole lot more of my photos.</p>
<p>In the evening we headed to the Fortune Theater to see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation_Mincemeat_(musical)">Operation Mincemeat</a> at the recommendation of several friends. It's a <em>fantastic</em> musical telling the story of a real British covert operation that took place during World War II. A cast of five take on <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/@mincemeatbway/video/7538109771023453462">86 roles</a>, sometimes switching roles live on stage multiple times during a single number. It's hilarious, touching, deeply entertaining and manages to start at high energy and then continually escalate that energy as the show continues.</p>
<p>The original British cast (three of whom co-wrote it) have moved to New York for a broadway production that started in March. The cast we saw in London were outstanding.</p>
<p>It's a tiny theater - the West End's second smallest at 432 seats (the smallest is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arts_Theatre">Arts Theater</a> at 350) which makes for an intimate performance.</p>
<p>I absolutely loved it and would jump at the chance to see it again.</p>
    
        <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/london">london</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/museums">museums</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/theatre">theatre</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 18:51:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Quoting Bruce Schneier</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Aug/27/bruce-schneier/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<blockquote cite="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2025/08/we-are-still-unable-to-secure-llms-from-malicious-inputs.html"><p>We simply don’t know to defend against these attacks. We have zero agentic AI systems that are secure against these attacks. Any AI that is working in an adversarial environment—and by this I mean that it may encounter untrusted training data or input—is vulnerable to prompt injection. It’s an existential problem that, near as I can tell, most people developing these technologies are just pretending isn’t there.</p></blockquote>
<p class="cite">&mdash; <a href="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2025/08/we-are-still-unable-to-secure-llms-from-malicious-inputs.html">Bruce Schneier</a></p>

    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/prompt-injection">prompt-injection</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/security">security</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/bruce-schneier">bruce-schneier</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai-agents">ai-agents</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 17:48:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Piloting Claude for Chrome</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Aug/26/piloting-claude-for-chrome/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-for-chrome">Piloting Claude for Chrome</a></strong></p>
Two days ago <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Aug/25/agentic-browser-security/">I said</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I strongly expect that the <em>entire concept</em> of an agentic browser extension is fatally flawed and cannot be built safely.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Today Anthropic announced their own take on this pattern, implemented as an invite-only preview Chrome extension.</p>
<p>To their credit, the majority of the <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-for-chrome">blog post</a> and accompanying <a href="https://support.anthropic.com/en/articles/12012173-getting-started-with-claude-for-chrome">support article</a> is information about the security risks. From their post:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Just as people encounter phishing attempts in their inboxes, browser-using AIs face prompt injection attacks—where malicious actors hide instructions in websites, emails, or documents to trick AIs into harmful actions without users' knowledge (like hidden text saying "disregard previous instructions and do [malicious action] instead").</p>
<p>Prompt injection attacks can cause AIs to delete files, steal data, or make financial transactions. This isn't speculation: we’ve run “red-teaming” experiments to test Claude for Chrome and, without mitigations, we’ve found some concerning results.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Their 123 adversarial prompt injection test cases saw a 23.6% attack success rate when operating in "autonomous mode". They added mitigations:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When we added safety mitigations to autonomous mode, we reduced the attack success rate of 23.6% to 11.2%</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I would argue that 11.2% is still a catastrophic failure rate. In the absence of 100% reliable protection I have trouble imagining a world in which it's a good idea to unleash this pattern.</p>
<p>Anthropic don't recommend autonomous mode - where the extension can act without human intervention. Their default configuration instead requires users to be much more hands-on:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li><strong>Site-level permissions</strong>: Users can grant or revoke Claude's access to specific websites at any time in the Settings.</li>
<li><strong>Action confirmations</strong>: Claude asks users before taking high-risk actions like publishing, purchasing, or sharing personal data.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>I really hate being stop energy on this topic. The demand for browser automation driven by LLMs is significant, and I can see why. Anthropic's approach here is the most open-eyed I've seen yet but it still feels doomed to failure to me.</p>
<p>I don't think it's reasonable to expect end users to make good decisions about the security risks of this pattern.


    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/browsers">browsers</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/chrome">chrome</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/security">security</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/prompt-injection">prompt-injection</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/llms">llms</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/anthropic">anthropic</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/claude">claude</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai-agents">ai-agents</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 22:43:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Will Smith’s concert crowds are real, but AI is blurring the lines</title><link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Aug/26/will-smiths-concert-crowds/#atom-everything</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong><a href="https://waxy.org/2025/08/will-smiths-concert-crowds-were-real-but-ai-is-blurring-the-lines/">Will Smith’s concert crowds are real, but AI is blurring the lines</a></strong></p>
Great piece from Andy Baio demonstrating quite how convoluted the usage ethics and backlash against generative AI has become.</p>
<p>Will Smith has been accused of using AI to misleadingly inflate the audience sizes of his recent tour. It looks like the audiences were real, but the combined usage of static-image-to-video models by his team with YouTube's ugly new compression experiments gave the resulting footage an uncanny valley effect that lead to widespread doubts over the veracity of the content.


    <p>Tags: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/andy-baio">andy-baio</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai">ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/generative-ai">generative-ai</a>, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai-ethics">ai-ethics</a></p>]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 03:50:49 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>