<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>The Pragmatic Engineer</title><link>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/xavwe/rss-aggregator/refs/heads/main/feeds/the-pragmatic-engineer-942a0ad4.xml</link><description>Archived feed from https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/rss/</description><item><title>Creative ways to fund open source projects</title><link>https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/creative-ways-to-fund-open-source-projects/</link><description><![CDATA[“Open source maintenance fee” trialed by Wix Toolset, while the creator of uv offers paid, enterprise-only features for larger companies.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 16:46:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New trend: extreme hours at AI startups</title><link>https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/new-trend-extreme-hours-at-ai-startups/</link><description><![CDATA[Pulling 80+ hour work weeks – including weekends – is becoming the norm across AI startups, and is unlikely to stop while AI is so hot.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 16:35:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cursor makes developers less effective?</title><link>https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/cursor-makes-developers-less-effective/</link><description><![CDATA[A study into the workflows of experienced developers found that devs who use Cursor for bugfixes are around 19% slower than devs who use no AI tools at all. One possible takeaway is that AI tools can be harder work than we’re led to believe.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 18:09:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Pulse: Section 174 is reversed! Mostly, that is</title><link>https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/the-pulse-section-174-is-reversed-mostly-that-is/</link><description><![CDATA[Finally, relief: tax regulation hurting the US tech industry is striked off for good - for the most part, that is.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 16:44:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Software engineering with LLMs in 2025: temperature check</title><link>https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/software-engineering-with-llms-in-2025/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>How are devs using AI tools at Big Tech and startups, and what do they actually think of them? This was the topic of my <a href="https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/now/#annual-conference-talk" rel="noreferrer">annual conference talk</a>, in June 2025, in London, at <a href="https://leaddev.com/leaddev-london/?ref=blog.pragmaticengineer.com" rel="noreferrer">LDX3 by LeadDe</a>v. </p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/content/images/2025/07/LDX3_Day1_CC_00147.jpg" class="kg-image" alt loading="lazy" width="2000" height="1334" srcset="https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/07/LDX3_Day1_CC_00147.jpg 600w, https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/07/LDX3_Day1_CC_00147.jpg 1000w, https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/07/LDX3_Day1_CC_00147.jpg 1600w, https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/07/LDX3_Day1_CC_00147.jpg 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption><span style="white-space: pre-wrap;">At LDX3 by LeadDev</span></figcaption></figure><p>To research, I talked with devs at:</p><ul><li><strong>AI</strong></li></ul>]]></description><pubDate>Sat, 5 Jul 2025 13:49:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Builder.ai did not “fake AI with 700 engineers”</title><link>https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/builder-ai-did-not-fake-ai/</link><description><![CDATA[The claim that the AI startup “faked AI” with hundreds of engineers went viral – and I also fell for it, initially. The reality is much more sobering: Builder.ai built a code generator on top of Claude and other LLMs; it did not build a so-called “Mechanical Turk.”]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 16:39:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Stack overflow is almost dead</title><link>https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/stack-overflow-is-almost-dead/</link><description><![CDATA[Today, Stack overflow has almost as few questions asked per month, as when it launched back in 2009. A recap of its slow, then rapid, downfall.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 15:29:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tech hiring: is this an inflection point?</title><link>https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/tech-hiring-is-this-an-inflection-point/</link><description><![CDATA[We might be seeing the end of remote coding interviews as we know them, and a return of in-person interviews, trial days and longer trial periods. Could hiring be returning to pre-pandemic norms?]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 16:03:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Survey: What’s in your tech stack?</title><link>https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/survey-whats-in-your-tech-stack/</link><description><![CDATA[We want to capture an accurate snapshot of software engineering, today – and need your help! Tell us about your tech stack and get early access to the final report, plus extra analysis]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 16:53:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Software engineering job openings hit five-year low?</title><link>https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/software-engineer-jobs-five-year-low/</link><description><![CDATA[There are 35% fewer software developer job listings on Indeed today, than five years ago. Compared to other industries, job listings for software engineers grew much more in 2021-2022, but have declined much faster since. A look into possible reasons for this, and what could come next.]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 20:27:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Where did TikTok’s software engineers go?</title><link>https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/where-did-tiktoks-software-engineers-go/</link><description><![CDATA[How has this uncertainty affected software engineers at the Chinese-owned social network?]]></description><pubDate>Thu, 6 Feb 2025 17:17:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Pragmatic Engineer 100K Giveaway</title><link>https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/the-pragmatic-engineer-100k-giveaway/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>The Pragmatic Engineer&apos;s YouTube channel crossed 100K subscribers. Celebrating with a giveaway of 100 books and newsletter subs:</p><ul><li>10x signed physical books (The Software Engineer&#x2019;s Guidebook [in English or German - your choice!], Building Mobile Apps at Scale; winners get both; shipping is on me)</li><li>90x</li></ul>]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 5 Feb 2025 15:36:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Are LLMs making StackOverflow irrelevant?</title><link>https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/are-llms-making-stackoverflow-irrelevant/</link><description><![CDATA[Fresh data shows that the number of questions asked on StackOverflow are as low as they were back in 2009 – which was when StackOverflow was one years old. The drop suggests that ChatGPT – and LLMs – managed to make StackOverflow’s business model irrelevant in about two years’ time.]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2025 17:28:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Where to find to The Pragmatic Engineer Podcast</title><link>https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/the-pragmatic-engineer-podcast/</link><description><![CDATA[<p>The Pragmatic Engineer Podcast covers software engineering at Big Tech and startups, from the inside. We do deepdives with experienced engineers and tech professionals who share their hard-earned lessons, interesting stories and advice they have on building software. </p><p>After each episode, you&#x2019;ll walk away with pragmatic approaches you</p>]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 8 Jan 2025 11:15:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why my new audiobook “The Software Engineer&apos;s Guidebook” is everywhere except on Audible</title><link>https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/why-my-audibook-is-not-on-audible/</link><description><![CDATA[Currently, Audible’s position is hurting audiobook authors. My audiobook isn’t on Audible due to a mix of their monopolistic pricing practices, and the company’s own complacency in how long they take to approve new titles.]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 17:41:24 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>